<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The countrie gentleman moderator Collections of such intermarriages, as haue beene betweene the two royall lines of England and Spaine, since the Conquest: with a short view of the stories of the liues of those princes. And also some obseruations of the passages: with diuers reasons to moderate the country peoples passions, feares, and expostulations, concerning the Prince his royall match and state affaires. Composed and collected by Edm. Garrard.</title>
            <author>Garrard, Edmund.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 130 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01503</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11624</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102860</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838622</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838622</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3007</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01503)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3007)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 958:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The countrie gentleman moderator Collections of such intermarriages, as haue beene betweene the two royall lines of England and Spaine, since the Conquest: with a short view of the stories of the liues of those princes. And also some obseruations of the passages: with diuers reasons to moderate the country peoples passions, feares, and expostulations, concerning the Prince his royall match and state affaires. Composed and collected by Edm. Garrard.</title>
                  <author>Garrard, Edmund.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 67, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edward All-de,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Variant: A2 (dedication) cancelled.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marriages of royalty and nobility --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Marriages of royalty and nobility --  Spain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  Spain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3007:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3007:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE COVNTRIE GENTLEMAN MODERATOR.</p>
            <p>Collections Of ſuch intermarriages, as haue beene betweene the two Royall Lines of ENGLAND and SPAINE, ſince the Conqueſt: with a ſhort view of the Stories of the liues of thoſe Princes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And alſo ſome obſeruations of the paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: with diuers reaſons to moderate the Country peoples paſsions, feares, and expoſtulations, concerning</hi> the Prince his Royall Match and State affaires.</p>
            <p>Compoſed and collected by <hi>Edm. Garrard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Edward All-de.</hi> 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3007:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3007:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, <hi>HENRY Lord</hi> DANVERS, <hi>Baron of Daunteſey.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONORABLE,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F I (poore and infortunate) ſhould ſay, that I can no more forget your Noble houſe, I ſo long followed, and many Noble fauours from thence receiued: then the children of Captiuity, could forget their owne <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> if I ſhould tell your Lorſhip how much I honour you, ioy at your ſight, memory, and happines, liberally proteſting all this, and much more; it may be thought but ſuperficiall, and the common phraſe of indigent men: But God that knoweth the ſecrets of all mens hearts, can witnes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mine, it ſincerely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth: If I could doe any thing worthy accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, I humbly acknowledge, it is due to your Lordſhip; yet howſoeuer, I here make bolde to put out vnder your Honourable Patronage, theſe my poore endeuours.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3007:3"/>
            <p> Firſt, the Title is ſome way ſutable to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition your Lordſhip now liueth in, as being (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede) more a Country Lord then a Court: If the Fate and State ſhall pleaſe to haue it otherwiſe, <hi>(Tam marti quam Mercurio)</hi> for the ſeruice of the King, and Countrey, amongſt the reſt of the Starres placed in that Spheare, your Lordſhip would at leaſt contribute light: but your daily relieuing of many poore in the Country, where and for which your renowne is, done more to Gods glory then your owne; your Lordſhips preferment will be in a better Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Subiect &amp; Treatiſe are likewiſe agreeable to your Lordſhips loyall diſpoſition, which is only deſiring God may be truly honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, all things ſute and ſucceede to the compleat comfort, contentment, &amp; good of the King, Prince and Kingdome: if they amongſt their ſerious af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, ſhall vouchſafe to looke into this worke. I humbly deſire the motiue thereof might bee as from your Lordſhip, receiuing your fauourable acceptance, pardon for this my boldnes, and to liue eſteemed</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips euer deuoted ſeruant,</hi> Edm. Garrard.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3007:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Intend by Gods helpe, and your patience (gentle Reader) to preſent vnto your view an Abſtract of ſuch intermariages as haue bin betweene the two royall Lines of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> and ſome other paſſages betwixt the two Nations, from the time of the Conqueſt, vntill this preſent: the ſubiect appropriating to that which is now moſt autentick on <hi>Englands</hi> faire ſtage, &amp; of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt conſequence that hath been there theſe many years, therefore the greater, is both my aduenture and preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for that the ſame and ſuch great affaires of State, are not to be meddled withall or talked of, but with great caution and reuerence, or rather indeed not at all, vpon the former and accuſtomed courſes of reſtriction, of the vulgar in that particular, hauing bin a long time in councel conſulted of, &amp; now ſomeway publike: Theſe my endeauours being but meerely collectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s out of our Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Chronicles (as hiſtory) which is ſaid to be the witnes of time, the light of truth, the memoriall of life, &amp; report of antiquitie: with ſome other obſeruations concerning thoſe affaires, and in the countrie too much expoſtulated
<pb facs="tcp:3007:4"/>of, I hope I ſhall giue no cauſe of offence, taxe, nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception; hauing no affectation to talke or buſie my ſelfe in State affaires, nor minister more, but rather leſſe occaſion for others ſo to doe. But that I ſhould preſume to write in a buſineſſe of ſo great a conſequence, and of this nature, and the rather comming now ſo late, and not in ſo good a ſeaſon as formerly it would haue done, I may be ſubiect both to reproofe and taxe. Onely, I ſhall deſire the Iudiciall, and beſt affected <hi>(prima facie)</hi> not to iudge me; what followes comes from a Proteſtant pen, from one that wiſheth all may bee well, liueth in the countrie farre out of ſight, and almoſt out of hearing, from the helme where the affaires of State are ſteared: therefore more then by obſeruation, and what the countrie affoords is beyond my knowledge, neither ſent, nor ſet on to write or ſpeake, hauing neither thought, aime, nor expectation of preferment, (not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming to my ſelfe thereof any waies worthy) ſhould thinke my ſelfe happy, if I might as a Moderator ſome way quallifie paſſion that the Countrie people might not ſo much expoſtulate of our Princes Royall Match, and the affaires of State as now they doe. For that purpoſe it is only to them ſent, meant, and intended: hauing only treated of the paſſages of former times, concerning that affaire or others of State for the preſent or future, I neither haue, nor will meddle withall, as indeed not
<pb facs="tcp:3007:4"/>fitting for the common people ſo to doe: As they are farre from their knowledges and apprehenſions, ſo ſhould they bee likewiſe from their diſcourſes and expoſtulations, not to looke where Lyons wake or ſleepe: The actions of Princes not to be pryed into, but by ſuch as are in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie. Peraduenture ſome will ſay, that in this my Diſcourſe I haue beene ſquint-eyde, as not looking or bending my courſe any waies direct: thoſe who haue beene auerſe, and vnwilling for our Princes Royall Match, will taxe me for a temporizer, J conceaue J haue not magnified the <hi>Spaniards</hi> aboue meaſure, more or otherwiſe then our owne authors and other Writers affirme; ſo could J wiſh they ſhould not out of paſſion, and inuention, be detracted beyond merrit, and with thoſe that haue ſo much deſired our Princes Match, my ſelfe with them I ſhall not any waies ingratiate, I hope my honeſt plaine meaning and intentions, ſhall indici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally iustifie me against either. Will as a good ſubiect ought (wiſhing all the Countrie people would doe the like) only deſire God may be truly honoured, praying to him to direct all things for the best, his Maieſtie obeyed in all his Commands on earth, haue compleat content and comfort, and liue long to ſee his holy intentions take effect for the good of Chriſtendome, and not with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny farther expoſtulations to trouble our ſelues, but rely on Gods prouidence, the King and Princes wiſdomes,
<pb facs="tcp:3007:5"/>and integrities, letting them and thoſe that are in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie alone in the buſineſſe; neither feare nor doubt, that any thing will be done, which ſhall any waies im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire the honour of Religion, or generall good of the kingdome: The farther particulars, this my Epiſtle De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatory by way of anticipation, ſhall not relate, but the work it ſelfe ſhal make particuler demonſtration therof: What I haue here begun, ſome of better abilitie (if it pleaſe them) may ſupplie that wherein I haue beene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiue: theſe my poore endeauours, I humbly leaue to your conſiderations, &amp; my ſelfe to your fauourable cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: reſting</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, <hi>E. G.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3007:5"/>
            <head>ENGLAND AND SPAINES INTERMARRIAGES, with a briefe tract of the ſtorie of thoſe <hi>Princes concerning thoſe</hi> affaires.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Reſcription and precedents, ſwaying with the poſitiue lawes of the Kingdome, they may then farre better ouer-rule, or at leaſt giue Reall ſatisfaction, in point of meere conceit, and late conceiued diſaffection: rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our owne Annalles and Chronicles, we ſhall there finde many mutuall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marriages, to haue beene betweene the two Royall Crownes, of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> began in the very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancie of our Monarchy, running in a long diſcent, chayned and linked together one with another, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king as it were a golden Orbe and circle of ſincere Princely loue and amity: ſo that many mighty Kings of <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>Portingale,</hi> haue had Royall mothers of the Engliſh Nation, and likewiſe many Royall Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes of <hi>Spaine,</hi> haue beene the bleſſed mothers of ſome puiſant, and victorious Kings of <hi>England.</hi> King <hi>William</hi> ſurnamed the conquerour, by whom <hi>England</hi> receiued his laſt ſubuerſion, and generall alteration,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3007:6"/>his courſes of gouernment, inſtitutions and lawes (by which wee are now gouerned) being exactly execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, were as linkes intermutually faſtned, made ſo ſtrong a Chaine, that it hath euer ſince held toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the whole frame of the ſtate in peace and order, as all the politique Regiments vpon earth, all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-leagued ſocieties of men, cannot ſhew a ſtraigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter forme of combination. This King firſt began, contracted <hi>Margaret</hi> his youngeſt daughter, to <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus</hi> King of <hi>Galicia:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1076.</note> 
               <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond lineally diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended from him, a famous and worthy King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> married <hi>Elenor</hi> his ſecond daughter, to another <hi>Alphonſus</hi> the ninth,<note place="margin">1171.</note> ſurnamed the good King of <hi>Caſtile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt, ſurnamed <hi>Cuer de Lyon,</hi> ſonne of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, he tooke to wife <hi>Berengaria,</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Sanctius</hi> King of <hi>Nauarr.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next intermarriage wee finde, to haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene thoſe two Nations being <hi>England,</hi> had there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a Queene (therein) And ſo for other in like ſort; I will be more particular; it was in the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Henry</hi> the third raigned 56. yeares.</note> who of all the Kings of <hi>England</hi> ſince the conqueſt, raigned longeſt, and his troubles there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the greateſt: not any wayes occaſioned by the marriage, but for that he would rule and gouerne, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his will, and luſts, and not by his lawes: thoſe that deſire to be more particularly informed thereof,<note place="margin">Stowe. Hollinſh. Speede.</note> the ſtory of his life written by many, will giue them further, and full ſatisfaction: for ſo much as ſhall concerne marriages, and other paſſages be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> I will onely contract my ſelfe.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:3007:6"/>
            <p> This King when he had raigned 39. yeares, with infinite and daily troubles, of ciuill warres, with his Barons, hee was ſuddainly called to another ſeruice from home. <hi>Alphonſo</hi> King of <hi>Spaine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The King of <hi>Spaine</hi> clai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Gaſcoyne.</hi>
               </note> claymed title to <hi>Gaſcoyne,</hi> by vertue of a Charter from <hi>Henry</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, confirmed by <hi>Richard</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> Kings of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. Henry</hi> the third, fearing the <hi>Gaſcoyners</hi> would draw in the Spaniards, peaceably as it were in the manner of a Progreſſe, repayred into <hi>Gaſcoyne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> went in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Gaſcoyney.</hi>
               </note> and from thence ſent Ambaſſadors to the King of <hi>Spayne,</hi> to deſire that the Lady <hi>Elenor</hi> his ſiſter, might bee giuen in marriage to his ſonne Prince <hi>Edward,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambaſſadors ſent into <hi>Spaine</hi> to treat of a marriage.</note> which was after <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt: this motion was well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued, beſides that they brought Letters Patents with them, from the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> in which amongſt all other clauſes, it was contained,<note place="margin">The King of <hi>Spaine</hi> relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his claime to <hi>Gaſconey.</hi>
               </note> that the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> did quit his claime, and whole right, which by vertue of any graunts, from <hi>Henry, Richard,</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> Kings of <hi>England,</hi> he had or ought to haue: here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon the King of <hi>England</hi> ſendeth both for his Queene, and his ſonne, (whom the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired,<note place="margin">The King of <hi>Spaine</hi> ſends for the Prince of <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> might be conuayed vnto him) onely with a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble intent, to ſee and doe him honour. Among other acts of ſincerity, and loue, <hi>Alphonſo</hi> ſent to the King of <hi>England</hi> good aduice, that after the example of good Kings and Princes, he ſhould be a Lamb to his Subiects, and Seruitors, and a Lyon vnto Aliens and Rebels.</p>
            <p>Soone after, the Queene and her ſonne arriuing in <hi>Gaſcoyne,</hi> when all things were rightly prepared, Prince <hi>Edward</hi> was thence preſently ſent into <hi>Spaine,</hi> where, at the Citie of <hi>Burges,</hi> he married the Lady <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:3007:7"/>ſiſter to the King with great honour,<note place="margin">The Prince of <hi>England</hi> marrieth with the King of <hi>Spaines</hi> ſiſter.</note> hauing firſt receiued Knighthood at his hands, which done returnes to <hi>Burdeux,</hi> from whence they altogether came ſafe, through <hi>Fraunce</hi> into <hi>England;</hi> the King of <hi>Fraunce</hi> being not long before returned from the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly land,<note place="margin">The Prince of <hi>England</hi> had great en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment in <hi>Fraunce.</hi>
               </note> gaue them both ſafe conduct in their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, and did to him and all his whole company, all the honour, with triumphes, and feaſts, which the wit of man, or the goodly Kingdome of <hi>Fraunce</hi> could afford: afterwards landed ſafely at <hi>Douer;</hi> what treaſure this noble young Princeſſe brought in portion to her husband, our Writers haue not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered vnto vs, but the king forthwith gaue to his ſonne <hi>Gaſcoyne, Ireland, Briſtowe, Stamford,</hi> and <hi>Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tham:</hi> King <hi>Henry</hi> liued after the marriage of his ſonne ſeauenteene yeares; during which time, this Spaniſh Lady carried her ſelfe,<note place="margin">The Spaniſh Lady a moſt vertuous Princeſſe.</note> as a moſt noble and worthy Princeſſe, and afterwards being Queene, a more renowned, loyall, and vertuous wife, no age euer afforded. This King <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt many his enterpriſes, of a Royall and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſolution, went in perſon to Warre againſt the Sarazenes: where that renowned and vertuous La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Elenor</hi> his wife, did endure with him an vnſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable companion of all his fortunes, and was at <hi>Acon</hi> deliuered of a daughter, there baptized by the name of <hi>Ione,</hi> ſhee is denoated by our owne. Writers, to be a matchleſſe precedent, of coniugall affection; the King her husband being trayterouſly wounded by a Sarazen, with a poyſoned knife, that when no me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine could extract the poyſon, this Lady <hi>Elenor</hi> (whileſt the King her husband ſlept.) With her
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3007:7"/>tongue daily licked his ranckling wounds, draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth the impoyſoned matter, that ſoone af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hee was fully cured, and ſhee fortunately pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued.</p>
            <p>The King and Queene not long after taking their iourney together towards <hi>Scotland,</hi> the Queene in her way thither-wards, ſickned and dyed in the yeare 1284. The king almoſt ſtruck dead with ſorrpw, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters his reſolution, returnes backe towards <hi>London,</hi> with a long and ſorrowfull iourney in a ſlowe and ſtately manner, ſhee being conuayed out of Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colnſhire towards <hi>London,</hi> in her honour, the king her husband, (who loued her aboue all worldly creatures) cauſed thoſe many famous Croſſes to bee erected, whereſoeuer her Royall corpes did reſt.<note place="margin">Charing Croſſe, <hi>at</hi> Waltham, <hi>St.</hi> Albones, <hi>and</hi> Dunſtable.</note> The King with his whole Nobility and Clergie, in a pompeous and Royall manner meetes the body at Saint <hi>Albones,</hi> and with a Noble and generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of his Subiects, brings it to the Royall Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulture of his Aunceſtors at <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> and there in Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Church, it was with all poſſible Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, and magnificence honourably interred. The King gaue vnto the Abbot there, twelue large and rich Lordſhips, charitably to giue Almes, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutly to pray for the bleſſed Queene, vntill the worlds end.</p>
            <p>Our owne Writers affirme of this Queene,<note place="margin">Speede. Walſing. Camdens Britania.</note> to our Nation ſhe was a louing mother: and ſaith one, the Columne and pillar (as it were of the whole Realme) ſhee added the vertues of a wife to her ſex; to them both, her immortall fame is a glory, and an honour to her Nation.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:3007:8"/>
            <p> King <hi>Edward</hi> the third,<note place="margin">1360.</note> married his daughter <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hanna</hi> to <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond King of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> ſonne of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus</hi> the 11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Gaunt</hi> Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> fourth ſonne of King <hi>Edward</hi> the third, did take to wife <hi>Conſtancia,</hi> eldeſt daughter of <hi>Peter</hi> King of <hi>Caſtile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To whom in right of his ſaid wife <hi>Conſtancia,</hi> the Kingdome of <hi>Caſtile</hi> and <hi>Leon,</hi> did diſcend, and they both ſtiled themſelues King and Queene of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> and <hi>Leon,</hi> which illuſtrious title is yet to be ſeene, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his noble monument in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Church in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Katherine</hi> the ſole daughter of the ſaid Duke of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> by his aforeſaid wife <hi>Conſtancia,</hi> was marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Henry,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1388.</note> the third ſonne of king <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Caſtile</hi> and <hi>Leon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Edmund</hi> Duke of <hi>Yorke,</hi> youngeſt ſonne of king <hi>Edward</hi> the third,<note place="margin">1391.</note> married <hi>Iſabella</hi> youngeſt daughter of <hi>Peter</hi> king of <hi>Caſtile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth married <hi>Iohanna</hi> the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Charles</hi> king of <hi>Nauarr.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1403.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The next intermarriage wee finde, betweene <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> was in the time of king <hi>Henry</hi> the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth, his owne marriage, his ſonnes with <hi>Spaine,</hi> and marriages of his daughters, are the greateſt acts of State, our Engliſh Annalles doe afford vs, firſt his owne marriage made a Vnion, whereupon after the effuſion of much bloud, to the conſumption of the greateſt part of the Engliſh Nobility, there fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, and euer ſince continued, a happy peace, and then by the marriage of his daughter, ſettled an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted and permanent ſucceſſion, for the Crowne
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3007:8"/>of <hi>England,</hi> the bleſſed happineſſe at this inſtant wee enioy. All which with the patience of the Reader, contrary to my intended reſolution, which was one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the ſtory of the Spaniſh matches, I will a little digreſſe, and briefly touch, hauing one with another dependancy and coherence.</p>
            <p>This king <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeauenth, for his wiſedome was ſaid to be a ſecond <hi>Salomon,</hi> and lay ſomewhat heauie on his people, and was Aunceſtor to our now Soueraigne, who will peraduenture ſome way, both for the mannaging of the State, and marriage of his children, make him a patterne, and precedent: But the difference is (the more is our happineſſe) <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeauenth his gathering of treaſure together, was to heape vp in ſtore, as appeared being found at <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> after his deceaſe vnder his owne key, and kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping eighteene hundred thouſand pounds ſterling. A huge maſſe of money for thoſe times. Our king hath expreſſed his Royall and Princely bounty, and expoſed his treaſure vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> important occaſions, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto his Maieſtie hath beene neceſſitated, gathered vp from his Subiects, but as ſhowers of raine, that falls backe vpon the earth againe. But it hath beene of late, and it is very like hence-forth it will be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to repay, ſupport, and ſupply.</p>
            <p>About the ninth yeare of king <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeauenth his raigne, there was one <hi>Peter Hyalus</hi> an Ambaſſador,<note place="margin">A Spaniſh Ambaſſadour ſent into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </note> ſent from <hi>Ferdinando</hi> and <hi>Iſabella</hi> king and Queene of <hi>Spaine,</hi> to treate of a marriage betweene <hi>Katherine</hi> their daughter, and Prince <hi>Arthur,</hi> ſonne and heire of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeauenth: it was obſerued this <hi>Hyalus</hi> was a man of great wiſedome, that through the preſent
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3007:9"/>could ſee farre into the future: which king <hi>Henry</hi> ſoone perceiued; <hi>Hyalus</hi> inſtantly became in great fauour and eſtimation with him, brought it ſo about, and yet not ſeene therein, that <hi>Hyalus</hi> was imployed for him into <hi>Scotland,</hi> both about a treaty of peace, as alſo a marriage for <hi>Margaret</hi> his eldeſt daughter with <hi>Iames</hi> the fourth, then king of <hi>Scotland:</hi> it was not king <hi>Henry</hi> his courſe, to ſeeke peace at any Prince his hands: But it was conceiued hee did it then, as not louing the barren warres, which hee thought would not bee worth his charge: <hi>Hyalus</hi> ſo caried himſelfe in thoſe Ambaſſies, that it was his maſter-peece, which euer after gaue him the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme of an excellent workman, which ſhall bee hereafter more particularly related. The warres be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the king of <hi>England</hi> and the king of <hi>Scots,</hi> were then at the height, when <hi>Hyalus</hi> was ſent, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming as it were from the king and Queene of <hi>Spaine,</hi> as from friends, equally well affected to both parties, to mediate a peace betweene the two kings, of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> as alſo about a treaty, or ouerture, at leaſt of a marriage, which perhaps in their owne perſons would not haue beene ſo eaſily brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, the point of honour might therevnto giue impeachment. <hi>Hyalus</hi> ſo handled the point of his imployment, that immediately after, Biſhop <hi>Foxe</hi> was ſent as an Ambaſſadour into <hi>Scotland,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon followed an honourable truce, and ſhortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards a marriage concluded, betweene the king of <hi>Scots,</hi> and <hi>Margaret</hi> the eldeſt daughter of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeauenth king of <hi>England:</hi> ſo that Doctor <hi>Morton</hi> afterwards Cardinall, and this <hi>Peter Hyalus</hi> the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3007:9"/>Ambaſſadour, were two of the happieſt inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that euer were, the one for compoſing and contriuing the marriage betweene king <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeauenth, and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the eldeſt daughter of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, whereby the two houſes of <hi>Yorke</hi> and <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſter</hi> were vnited, and <hi>Hyalus</hi> a fore-runner of good hap, was therefore by ſome called an <hi>Elias,</hi> being the firſt motiue and ſpeciall meanes of the intermarriage betweene <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> whereby we enioy our now Soueraigne, whom God graunt long to raigne ouer vs.</p>
            <p>The Spaniards are obſerued generally to be acute and ingenious, and many of them of great wiſdome, and deepe iudgements, ſome reaſon thereof concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, for that they are freer from the dull diſceaſe of drinke, then other Nations are.</p>
            <p>The great Hiſtorians writes in this manner of them. The Spaniards are more able,<note place="margin">Guichardine. Biterus.</note> then either the French, or Germanes, to endure the actions of the body, and to ſuffer the paſſions of the minde. Their firſt founder was a Souldier, therefore are they held naturally the more for warre:<note place="margin">Jgnatius.</note> and no Nation hath euer beene therein more exerciſed. They haue a Spaniſh Prouerbe, <hi>To haue peace with England doth vs betide, warres with all the world beſide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe our auncient Writers affirme,<note place="margin">Droder. Siculus lib. <hi>6.</hi> Strabo lib. <hi>3.</hi> Mila lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> that the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard is moſt patient in want, hardneſſe, hunger, thirſt, heat, colde, and all other toyle and trouble, both of body and minde, and moſt ready and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, for loue of Country, or honour, to encounter all dangers whatſoeuer. For the laſt particular, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Spaniard hath that height of commendation
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3007:10"/>giuen him, it neither can be any detraction or dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution to the Engliſh; they haue deſerued as much: whereof the Spaniards themſelues haue had experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>The marriage with <hi>Spaine</hi> was almoſt ſeauen yeares in treaty,<note place="margin">The Spaniſh match ſeauen yeares in treaty.</note> which was in part cauſed, by the tender yeares of the marriage couple, eſpecially of the Prince: But the true reaſon was, that thoſe two Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, being Princes of great policie, and profound iudgement, ſtoode a great time, looking one vpon anothers fortunes how they would goe, knowing well that in the meane time the very treaty it ſelfe, gaue abroad in the world, a reputation of a ſtraite coniunction and amity betweene them, which ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued on both ſides to many purpoſes, that their ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall affaires required, and yet they continued ſtill free: But in the end, when the fortunes of both Princes did grow euery day more and more proſperous, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, and that looking about them, they ſaw no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conditions, they ſhiſt it vp.</p>
            <p>The ſecond day of October,<note place="margin">Queene <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therine</hi> arriued in <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> in the 17. yeare of the kings raigne, the Lady <hi>Katherine,</hi> daughter to <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nand,</hi> and <hi>Izabella</hi> king and Queene of <hi>Spaine,</hi> arriued in <hi>England</hi> at <hi>Plymouth,</hi> and ſhe was married to Prince <hi>Arthur</hi> in <hi>Pauls,</hi> the 14. day of Nouember following; the Prince being about 15. yeares of age, and the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy 18. The manner of her receiuing, the manner of her entry into <hi>London,</hi> and the celebration of their marriage were performed, with great and true mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence, in regard of coſt and order. The chiefe man that tooke the care, was Biſhop <hi>Fox,</hi> who was not onely a great Councellour for warre, or peace,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3007:10"/>but alſo a good Suruayor of works, and a good Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of ceremonies, and any thing that was fit, for the actiue part belonging to the ſeruice of a Court, or State of a great king.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the deuices, and conceits of the try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphes at the marriage, there was a great deale of <hi>Aſtronomy:</hi> the Lady being reſembled to <hi>Heſperus,</hi> and the Prince to <hi>Arcturus:</hi> and the olde king <hi>Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> that was the great Aſtronomer of kings (and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtor to the Lady) was brought in to be Fortune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teller of the match: And whoſoeuer had thoſe toyes in compyling, they were not altogether pedanticall. But we may be ſure, that king <hi>Arthur</hi> the Brittaine (in whoſe acts were worth enough to make him famous, beſides that which is fabulous written of him:) the Prince his diſcent from him, and the Lady <hi>Katherine</hi> from the houſe of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> was not forgotten; thoſe two particulars had a great part in the play: But it ſeemes, it is not good to fetch fortune from the Starres. This young prince <hi>Arthur,</hi> drow vpon him not onely the hopes and affections of his Country, but the eyes and expectations of Forraigners, all fruſtrated, enioying him ſo little a time, as they did, the great alterations, and ſtrange euents afterwards enſuing.</p>
            <p>The marriage portion the Princeſſe brought,<note place="margin">The marriage portion.</note> which was turned ouer to the King, by renunciation, was two hundred thouſand Duckets, whereof one hundred thouſand were payd ten dayes after the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnization of the marriage, and the other hundred thouſand, at two payments annuall; but part of it in Iewels, and Plate, and a due courſe ſet downe to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3007:11"/>haue them iuſtly, and indifferently priſed.</p>
            <p>The Ioyncture,<note place="margin">Queene <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therines</hi> Ioin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture.</note> or the aduancement of the Lady, was the third part of the principalitie of <hi>Wales,</hi> and of the Dukedome of <hi>Cornwall,</hi> and the Earledome of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> to be after ſet forth in ſeueraltie; and in caſe ſhe came to be Queene of <hi>England;</hi> her aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was left indiffinite, but that it ſhould be as great, as any former Queene of <hi>England</hi> had: Prince <hi>Arthur,</hi> imediately after the Solemnization of the Mariage, was ſent to keepe his reſcyance and Court, as Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> at the Caſtle of <hi>Ludlowe:</hi> after a few moneths, in the beginuing of Aprill, he there deceaſed;<note place="margin">Prince <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur</hi> deceaſed.</note> So that in reſpect he dyed ſo young, and by reaſon of his Fathers manner of education, that did caſt no great Luſtre vpon his children, there is little particular mention of him, onely thus much remaineth, that he was very ſtudious and learned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond his yeares, and beyond the cuſtome of great Princes.</p>
            <p>The February next following, <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Yorke,</hi> afterward <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight, was created Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> and Earle of <hi>Cheſter;</hi> For the Dukedome of <hi>Cornewall,</hi> deuolued vnto him by Statute, which was halfe a yeares diſtance taken for his creation, and his Prince <hi>Arthurs</hi> death, which was conſtrued to be, to exprect a full time, whereby it might appeare, whether the Lady <hi>Katherine</hi> were with childe by Prince <hi>Arthur</hi> or not; when this doubt was cleered, <hi>Henry</hi> the Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> was preſently Contracted to the Lady <hi>Katherine</hi> his brother Prince <hi>Arthurs</hi> Widow, the reaſon of the Kings ſo doing, ſome Writers affirme, was becauſe he was cloſe handed,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3007:11"/>and would not part with a ſecond Dowrie; ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers affirme (and it is like they are neereſt the truth) out of his affection to <hi>Ferdinando</hi> King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> with whom he had euer a conſent, euen in nature and cuſtomes, and out of a politicke conſideration, to continue his alyance with <hi>Spaine,</hi> being aſſured, that the Lady was of a moſt worthy, vertuous, and Princely diſpoſition, and in his profound iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, knew that wiues were caſuall commodities, both for the loue he bore to his Sonne, and the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; for that neither of them ſhould runne ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hazzard, reteyned the Lady to be Queene of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next inſtantly taken in hand,<note place="margin">The King of <hi>Scotlands</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage with the Kings el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, done by <hi>Proxie.</hi>
               </note> was the worke begun by <hi>Hyalus</hi> the Spaniſh Embaſſador, the Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nization of the Spowſals of <hi>Iames</hi> the Fourth, King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> with the Lady <hi>Margarel</hi> the Kings eldeſt Daughter, which was done by <hi>Proxie,</hi> and publiſhed at <hi>Pauls</hi> Croſſe, the 25. day of Ianuary, and <hi>Te Deum</hi> ſolemnly ſung; But certaine it is, that the ioy of the Citie thereupon ſhewed by ringing the Bells, and Bonfiers, and ſuch other incenſe of the people, was more then could be expected, in caſe of ſo great and freſh enmitie betweene the Nations, eſpecially in <hi>London,</hi> which were far enough from the feeling any the former calamities of the Warre, and therefore might be truly attributed to a ſecret inſtinct, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring, (which many times runneth not onely in the hearts of Princes) but in the pulſes and veines of people) touching the happineſſe there to enſue in time to come.</p>
            <p>The Mariage was in Auguſt following conſuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3007:12"/>at <hi>Edenborough,</hi> King <hi>Henry</hi> bringing his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as farre as <hi>Colliweſton</hi> on the way, and then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning her to the attendance of the Earle of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland,</hi> who with a great troope of Lords and Ladies of Honour, brought her into <hi>Scotland</hi> to the King her Husband.</p>
            <p>This Mariage had beene in treatie by the ſpace al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of three yeares, from the time that <hi>Hyalus</hi> made the firſt ouerture, and that the King of <hi>Scotland</hi> ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after, opened his minde to Biſhop <hi>Foxe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſumme giuen in mariage portion by the King,<note place="margin">The Mariage portion.</note> was ten thouſand pounds. The ioyncture and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement aſſured by the King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> was two thouſand pounds a yeare, after King <hi>Iames</hi> his death, one thouſand pounds a yeare in preſent, for the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies maintenance. This to be ſet forth in lands of the beſt, and moſt certaine Reuenue.</p>
            <p>The King as it is reported,<note place="margin">A queſtion propoſed by the Lords of the Counſell.</note> before this Match was concluded, propoſed it to his Councell, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them it was debated, ſome of the Table, in the Freedome of Councellours (the King being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent) did put the caſe, that if God ſhould take away the Kings two Sonnes without iſſue, that then the kingdome of <hi>England</hi> would fall vnto the King of <hi>Scotland,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The. Kings Reply.</note> which might preiudiſe the Monarchie of <hi>England:</hi> whereunto the King himſelfe replyed, that if that ſhould be, <hi>Scotland</hi> would be but an acceſſion to <hi>England,</hi> and not <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Scotland,</hi> for that the greater would draw the leſſe; and that it was a ſafer Vnion for <hi>England</hi> then that of <hi>France;</hi> This paſſed as an Oracle, and ſilenced thoſe that moued the queſtion; This was a kinde of diuine and propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3007:12"/>propoſition, made by the Lords of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, and ſo accordingly anſwered by the King; ſo that the ſaid <hi>Iames</hi> the fourth King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> had iſſue by the Lady <hi>Margaret, Iames</hi> the Fift,<note place="margin">The Kings Diſcent.</note> and he had iſſue Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> ſhe had iſſue our now Soueraigne; ſo that he is great Grandchilde of <hi>Margaret,</hi> eldeſt Daughter to <hi>Henry</hi> the Seauenth.</p>
            <p>Now ſeeing I haue gone thus farre in matters of Mariage, contrary to my intent, as not to haue med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with any but thoſe of <hi>Spaine,</hi> I will now goe through by way of touch, rather then by ample diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, of the mariage of the laſt, and indeed of all the Daughters and children of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Henry</hi> the Seauenth contracteth <hi>Mary</hi> his youngeſt Daughter to the Emperor.</note> and the rather, for that it was the laſt act, that concluded his temporall felicitie, which was the concluſion of a glorious match, betweene his Daughter <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Charles,</hi> Princes of <hi>Caſtyle;</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the great Emperour, both being of tender yeares (which treatie was perfected by Biſhop <hi>Foxe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Henry</hi> the Seauenth dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage tooke not effect.</note> and others his Commiſſioners at <hi>Calice.</hi>) But by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the King about ſome yeare after died, that mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age did not take effect;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mary</hi> King <hi>Henryes</hi> youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter married to the King of <hi>France.</hi> Afterwards to the Duke of <hi>Suffolke.</hi>
               </note> ſhe was afterwards maried to the King of <hi>France,</hi> who being aged, ſhortly after died, had no iſſue by her: King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight her brother ſent ouer into <hi>France, Charles Brandon</hi> Duke of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> to fetch her from thence, who maried her, and by him ſhe had iſſue: the farther particulars in thoſe affaires, I leaue the readers, to the peruſall of the workes of many Writers,<note place="margin">Stowe. Holland. Speede.</note> that haue written the ſame at large.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Henry</hi> the Seauenth I will conclude, being he himſelfe by the generall concluder of all, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3007:13"/>(Only this) he had the fotune of a true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, aſwell as of a great King,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ote.</note> in liuing exerciſed, and dying repentant, his happineſſe was much the more; as when he left the world, was in great felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie (being as it were at the top of all worldly bliſſe) in regard of the high mariages of his Children, his great renowne (throughout Europe) his great Riches, and the perpetuall conſtancie of his proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſucceſſes, all which were ſome way a ſhadow and vaile; that it did not ſo euidently appeare, as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe it would, in what obloquie of the people, (he notwithſtanding liued.) So that death to him was wonderfull opportune, to withdrawe, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue him from any future blow of Fortune, which in all likelyhood would haue fallen vpon him, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the great hatred of his people; and the Title of his Sonne, being then come to eighteene yeares of age, and being a bold Prince, and liberall, gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vpon the people, by his very aſpect and preſence.</p>
            <p>The King according to the contract made by his Father,<note place="margin">King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Lady <hi>Katherine,</hi> his brothers wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow.</note> married his Brother Prince <hi>Arthurs</hi> Widow. The ſecret prouidence of God ordaining that Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age to be the cauſe of great euents and changes: our Writers doe not lay it to the Ladies charge, that ſhe in her particuler miniſtered any occaſion thereof.</p>
            <p>The ſtorie of the Kings life, more or otherwiſe then it ſhall concerne the diuorce; the Ladies life and conuerſation, I will not here meddle; many haue written of him at large, but the leſſe is the more, for his commendation:<note place="margin">Queene <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therine</hi> liued twenty years with the King</note> When this Lady had liued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue twenty yeares with the King, as a vertuous and loyall Wife, Cardinall <hi>Wolſey</hi> we finde had a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3007:13"/>great part in this play, whoſe diſcent <hi>Pollidor Vigill</hi> relateth, <hi>Parentem habuit virum probum at lanium,</hi> had an honeſt man to his Father, but a Butcher: then for the particular ſtory of his life, more then ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne this affaire, I leaue the Readers to many other Authors that haue written the ſame at large; but in briefe, he was intollerable wicked, pompous, and magnificent, and according to the fate (commonly of ſuch men) his end was infamous and infortunate; vpon ſome priuate grudge he bore to Queene <hi>Kathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine,</hi> partly to be reuenged thereby vpon her Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew the Emperour, becauſe he would not make him Pope (as ſecretly he had requeſted him) and partly becauſe often-times in a moſt ſecret, louing, and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle faſhion, ſhe had admoniſhed and warned him of his couetouſneſſe, tyranny; of his extortions, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions; of his pride and licentious courſe of life; ſuch men, when they are told of thoſe things, being eminent and powerfull, vſually will extend it to the higheſt, to execute their malice; which <hi>Wolſey</hi> ſo did towards the Queene, as it afterwards fell out to bee apparant, that to the King in priuate hee had caſt ſome ſcruples, with ſome ſubtle diſputations, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the lawfulneſſe, and nullitie of the Kings mariage, who hauing (as it ſeemed) a deſire to change, as by his hauing ſo many Wiues, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it was ſomewhat probable, made a great ſhew and expreſſure to the world, that he began to be ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ouer his conſcience, and prouident to eſtabliſh the true ſucceſſion of the kingdome, in a lawfull heire; ſtrucke ſo great an impreſſion into him, and ſo buſied his cogitations and thoughts, that a religious
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3007:14"/>ſorrow began to ſeaze vpon him (and to auoide the continuance in that inceſtuous ſinne) vntill by a iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall ſentence, the doubts were cleered, he refrained from the Queenes bed; and the Cardinall to make himſelfe more great then he was, procured a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from the Pope, to be directed to him, and to his ancient brother Cardinall <hi>Campeius,</hi> that before them as ſupreme Iudges, that queſtion (by legall proceſſe and proceedings) might be heard, debated on, and cenſured, according to the lawes of God.</p>
            <p>Theſe two Legates (hauing receiued their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion) informeth the Queene of their authoritie and power, and ſhe in ſome paſſion accuſed <hi>Wolſey,</hi> as the principall brocher of that doubt, and a main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainer of that contention, which he denied, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed himſelfe. The King pretending nothing in this buſineſſe but truth, ſinceritie, and Iuſtice, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Lawes of God and man, was well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, that the Queene ſhould make choyſe of the greateſt Clerkes, and the beſt learned men in the kingdome, to defend, and maintaine her cauſe, which ſhe accordingly did,<note place="margin">Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners choſen by the Queene.</note> as namely, <hi>William War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> then Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and <hi>Nicholas Weſt</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ely, Iohn Fiſher</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> and <hi>Henry Standiſh</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Aſſoph.</hi> For the proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of this buſineſſe, a ſtately Court was crected in the great Hall at the <hi>Black-Friers,</hi> where the two Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates ſate as Iudges, the King and Queene ſcited in their owne perſons, or by their Procters to appeare. The King by his Procter ſubmitted himſelfe to the Apoſtulation authority and power, which by the Pope to the two Legates was giuen: But the Queene
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3007:14"/>her ſelfe (accompanied with many Lords, Knights, Ladies, Gentlemen and Gentlewomen) and hauing firſt done great reuerence to the two Legates) ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed from them (as from Iudges, which were not compotent, and indifferent, to determine betwixt the Queene and King) to the Court at <hi>Rome;</hi> This appeale they allowed not, but in the ſame Court they ſate weekely, and before them many learned and ſubtill Diſputations, touching the lawfulneſſe; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo concerning the inſufficiencie of that Mariage, were daily made before them.</p>
            <p>The King perceiuing, that no quicke diſpatch was vſed, though oftentimes they deliberately conſulted, came with the Queene into the ſaid Court, where his Maieſtie ſolemnly proteſted his infinite loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her, acknowledging her to be the moſt amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,<note place="margin">The Kings proteſtation and loue to the Queene.</note> louing, kinde, dutious, modeſt, and ſweeteſt Wife, that he thought was in the world; and that therefore he ſhould not take ſo much ioy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in any thing elſe whatſoeuer, as he ſhould doe in her; if by the lawes of God and man, ſhe might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine his Wife, and therefore for the determining of that queſtion, and for the quieting of his troubled conſcience, he inſtantly importuned a quicke di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatch, and a finall end.</p>
            <p>Then was the Queene demanded, whether ſhee would ſticke to her appeale or no, who anſwered yea, yet for all that, the Court proceeded weekely, though ſoftly, as before.</p>
            <p>The Queene preſently roſe vp, and going about the Court to the King, fell downe on her knees be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his feete, and in the hearing of the people ſpake
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3007:15"/>thus in effect;<note place="margin">The Queens ſpeech to the King.</note> Sir, I deſire you to take ſome pitty vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me; and doe me iuſtice and right: I am a poore Woman, a ſtranger borne out of your Dominions, hauing here no indifferent counſell, and leſſe aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of friendſhip! alas, wherein haue I offended, or what cauſe of diſpleaſure haue I giuen, that you intend to put me away? I take God to my iudge, I haue beene to you a true and humble wife, euer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to your will and pleaſure, neuer gainſaying any thing wherein you tooke delight: without all grudge, or diſcontented countenance, I haue loued all them that haue loued you, howſoeuer their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections haue beene to me-ward: I haue borne you children and beene your wife, now this twenty years. Of my virginity and mariage bed, I make God and your owne conſcience the iudge, and if it be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe proued, I am content to be put from you with ſhame: The King your father in his time for his wife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, was knowne to be a ſecond <hi>Solomon,</hi> and <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinando</hi> of <hi>Spaine</hi> my Father the wiſeſt amongſt their kings; could they in this match be ſo farre ouerſeene, or are there now wiſer, and more learned men then at any time were? ſurely it ſeemeth wonderfull to me, that my mariage after twenty yeares ſhould be thus called in queſtion, with new inuention againſt me, who neuer intended but honeſtie; Alas Sir, I ſee I am wronged, hauing no Councell to ſpeake for me, but ſuch as are your ſubiects, and cannot be indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent on my part; therfore I moſt humbly beſeech you in charity ſtay this courſe, vntill I may haue aduiſe and counſell from <hi>Spaine;</hi> if not, your Graces plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure be done, and therewithall riſing, and making
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3007:15"/>lowly obeiſance to the Court, departed thence,<note place="margin">Queene <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therine</hi> depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Court.</note> lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vpon the arme of her ſeruant, deceiued each man, expecting ſhe had returned to her ſeate, when as ſhe tooke directly out of the place; which being perceiued, the Cryer againe called her by the name of Queene <hi>Katherine,</hi> to come into the Court; Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam quoth her guide, you are againe called; on ſaid ſhe, it maketh no matter, this is no indifferent Court for me, therefore goe forward.</p>
            <p>The King perceiuing that ſhe was departed,<note place="margin">The Kings report of the Queene.</note> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſpake thus vnto the aſſembly; I will (quoth he) in her abſence declare before you all, that ſhe hath beene to me a moſt true, obedient, and comfortable wiſe, endued with all vertuous qualities, conditions, according to her birth, and lowlineſſe, equalls any of the meaneſt eſtate.</p>
            <p>The Court ſate many times after, where many ſubtle and vebement allegations were vrged for the lawfulneſſe and nullity of the Mariage, the King ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly bent to haue an end, foreſaw he ſhould neuer there haue any: whileſt the buſineſſe was in debate and handling, he priuately imployed diuers Lords, and the greateſt Diuines within his kingdome, to trauaile into all the Vniuerſities in the Chriſtian world, and there to be reſolued of their opinions, touching the validitie or nullity of the mariage. And when they all returned, they brought with them twelue Inſtruments, ſealed with the publike Seales of ſo many of the Vniuerſities, and alſo the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſundry great and famous learned men:<note place="margin">The Kings mariage iudged vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull.</note> by all which it appeared, that they agreed and conſented in one, that the Kings mariage with his Brothers
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3007:16"/>wife was vtterly voyde, and contrary to the lawes of God and man, notwithſtanding the diſpenſation of the Pope.</p>
            <p>The King ſent thoſe Inſtruments vnto the Queene, deſiring to be ſatisfied from her, whether ſhe would yeeld her conſent to the Diuorce or no, for the qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eting of the Kings conſcience, to referre it to foure Prelates, and foure temporall Lords.</p>
            <p>The Queene thereunto made a long, graue, noble, and patient anſwer, poſitiuely concluding, ſhe would not ſubmit her ſelfe to any courſe therein: vntill the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> which was priuie to the beginning, had made there a determination and finall end: the King hauing ſeuerall times formerly ſent vnto the Pope, had beene long delayed, ſeeing no likelihood of an end, reſolued no longer to wait in his atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> went roundly and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely on in another courſe, ſummons a Parliament, there ſhewing the twelue Inſtruments from the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Vniuerſities,<note place="margin">The Kings Diuorce by act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> an Act paſſed, and his mariage with the Lady <hi>Katherine</hi> was diſſolued and made voide, a ſentence of Diuorce pronounced by the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and ſhe was euer after to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Queene <hi>Dowager:</hi> few or none but are either ſo farre read in our Engliſh Chronicles, or may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue what afterwards became of the Popes vſurped Heptarchie in England, and what further fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed.</p>
            <p>So here you haue heard the relation of the Story of this great Queene <hi>Katherine,</hi> though infortunate, was indeed, a mirrour and example of wiſedome, integritie, ſincerity, and all Royall and Princely
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3007:16"/>vertues. Yet it is vnlike, but that before her comming ouet into this kingdome, ſhe might be detractiuely expoſtulated of, and had not ſhe beene as ſhe is here diſcribed, (as the times afterwards were) ſhe would aſſuredly haue had her part of detraction from our Writers, as they haue beene ſome way ſparing of her due commendation.</p>
            <p>After her ſeparation and diuorce from the King, there is little newes of her, but that within ſome three yeares after at <hi>Kimbleton</hi> in the County of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tington,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Queene <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therine</hi> decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</note> ſhe there religiouſly liued and dyed, and lyeth interred in the Cathedrall Church of <hi>Peterborough.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next mariage betwixt <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> King <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond came ouer into <hi>England</hi> and married Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> Daughter to <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight, which he had by Queene <hi>Katherine</hi> of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Mariage is yet ſo freſh in memory, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the countrie people is indeed a great occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of producing thoſe feares and doubts, they ſeeme to apprehend, theſe things I muſt acknowledge, are too great a conſequence of State for me to meddle withall, yet vnder fauour as a Moderator, I would willingly the country people ſhould truly know and take it into their conſiderations, that for thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions in Queene <hi>Maryes</hi> time (it was thought) ſhe was much the more thereunto drawne by her two Biſhops, that were ſuch bloud-hounds (<hi>Gardener</hi> and <hi>Bonner</hi>) King <hi>Phillip</hi> was both a mediator, and Moderator, what he could, to ſtay them, the which with the ſtory of the mariage, and other paſſages concerning the ſame, I will here as our owne Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters haue affirmed, briefly and truely relate.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:3007:17"/>
            <p> Queene <hi>Mary</hi> her intent to marry with King <hi>Phillip,</hi> ſhe cauſed to be publiſhed: <hi>Stephen Gardener</hi> then Lord Chancellour, made a ſpeech to the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie in the Chamber of preſence, ſetting forth the honour, the riches, and augmentation of Titles to the Crowne of <hi>England;</hi> yet was it diſtaſtefull to many, great feares and doubts inſtantly conceaued would follow, as well the Church reformed, as for the pollitique, and State affaires of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>The firſt beginners of commotion were, <hi>Henry</hi> Duke of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> and Sir <hi>Thomas Wyat,</hi> making Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimations for the abandoning of ſtrangers, and to withſtand the Queenes mariage with King <hi>Philip,</hi> the reaſons they further alleaged and publiſhed, their proceedings and infortunate ends, I leaue the reader to the peruſall of their Stories by diuers Written at large.</p>
            <p>The Queene remoued to the Tower,<note place="margin">The Queens mariage con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by Parliament <hi>Anno.</hi> 2. <hi>Ca.</hi> 2. Some of the Nobility and Commons much diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented. The Queene ſent Letters to giue them ſome content</note> ſummons a Parliament, wherein by Statute the mariage was confirmed, to the great contentment, comfort and ioy, of the then time obſeruers. But ſome of the Nobilitie, and the Commons for the moſt part were much grieued and diſcontented thereat. Theſe diſtaſtiue ſtomacks, Queene <hi>Mary</hi> well perceauing, therefore to giue them the more content, ſhe ſent Letters ſigned with her owne hand into <hi>Wales,</hi> charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord Preſident, the Biſhop of <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Salisburie,</hi> to intimate the benefit therof to the whole land, as much as might be, and eſpecially <hi>London,</hi> whoſe Lord Maior and Commons were ſent for; to whom the Lord Chancellour made a Speech,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3007:17"/>told them how by the match, all the Realme would be much intiched,<note place="margin">The Londo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners became inſtantly for the mariage.</note> but eſpecially <hi>London</hi> by their Trade and Traffique with <hi>Spaine,</hi> that was enough, not only to alter and reduce, but to ſet them an edge beyond, or at leaſt equiuolent with all other reſpects, or conſiderations whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>The Earle of <hi>Bedford</hi> and the Lord <hi>Fitzwaters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">King <hi>Phillip</hi> ſent for.</note> were ſent into <hi>Spaine</hi> to conduct King <hi>Phillip</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> the Lord Admirall with twenty eight ſhips ſecuring the ſeas, the ſpace of three moneths before. All things thus ordered, and <hi>Phillip</hi> in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe, tooke ſhipping at <hi>Carone</hi> in <hi>Gallezia,</hi> and with a Nauie of an hundred and fiftie ſailed directed his courſe for the Queene; vpon Friday the twenty day of Iuly he arriued at <hi>Southampton,</hi>
               <note place="margin">King <hi>Phillip</hi> landed in <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> and was the firſt man of the Fleete that ſet ſoote on the ſhore, which no ſooner done, but he drew his Sword, and bare it naked in his hand as he went. The Earle of <hi>Arundle</hi> Steward of the Queenes houſe, preſented to his Highneſſe the <hi>George</hi> and <hi>Garter,</hi> and the Maior of the Towne of <hi>Southaempton</hi> the keyes of the Towne, thither was ſent the Lord Chancellour from the Queene, and he againe of his Nobles ſent to her (who was on the way to <hi>Wincheſter</hi> to welcome him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.) Towards which City vpon Munday following he ſet forth, being accompanied with the Marqueſſe of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> the Earles of <hi>Arundle, Darby, Worceſter, Bedford, Rutland, Penbroke,</hi> and <hi>Surry;</hi> the Lords <hi>Clynton, Cobham, Willoughbie, Darcy, Matreuers, Talbot, Strange, Fitz-warren,</hi> and <hi>North.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Spaniſh Nobles.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Spaniſh traine were the Dukes of <hi>Aluer</hi> and <hi>Medina Cellina</hi> the Admirall of <hi>Caſtilla,</hi> the Marqueſſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3007:18"/>of <hi>Bergnes Piſcara Sarra Valli Anguilar,</hi> the Earles of <hi>Egmonde, Horne, Peria, Chinchon, Oliuares, Saldana, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dela, Euente, Sallida, Landriano, Caſtellar,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Cuenca,</hi> and others, ſo that more honourable Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants had ſildome beene ſeene.</p>
            <p>Then there were Articles agreed on, which were branched out into tenne propoſitions, whereunto King <hi>Philip</hi> ſubſcribed, they were very honourable for <hi>England:</hi> the perticulars of them I leaue the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to Mr. <hi>Speede</hi> his excellent compendious worke, where the whole paſſages of this affaire, and theſe Articles are at large related.</p>
            <p>Then with the conſent of all parties,<note place="margin">The matriage of King <hi>Philip</hi> and Queene <hi>Mary. Anno</hi> 1554.</note> the marriage with great ſtate was ſolemnized at <hi>Wincheſter</hi> vpon Wedneſday, being the 25. of Iuly on Saint <hi>Iames</hi> day, where the Emperours Ambaſſadours preſently pronounced, that in conſideration of this marriage, their Maiſter had giuen vnto his ſonne <hi>Philip,</hi> the Kingdomes of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> whereupon their titles by <hi>Garter</hi> King at Armes, was ſolemnly proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with theſe ſtiles as followeth.</p>
            <p>Philip <hi>and</hi> Mary <hi>by the grace of God King and Queene of</hi> England, Fraunce, Naples, Ieruſalem <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>defender of the Faith, Princes of</hi> Spaine <hi>and</hi> Cicill, <hi>Archdukes of</hi> Auſtritch, <hi>Dukes of</hi> Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane, Burgundy, <hi>and</hi> Brabant, <hi>Counties of</hi> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpurge, Flaunders, <hi>and</hi> Tyroll.</p>
            <p>In Nouember following the marriage, the Queene was reported to haue bene conceiued with Childe:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3007:18"/>for ioy whereof, <hi>Te Deum</hi> was commaunded ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be ſung, and Proceſſions and Prayers made for her ſafe deliuerance. The Queene tooke her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, the Court was full of Midwiues and Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Attendants, Rockers were prouided, the Cradle prepared, and all made ſo certaine, that ſome were puniſhed for publiſhing doubts thereof to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, in ſo much as it paſſed in Parliament, that if God ſhould take away Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> their ſuppoſed young Maſter comming into the world,<note place="margin">So called by Sir <hi>Richard Southwell</hi> Knight of the houſe.</note> ſhould finde himſelfe prouided for. It was by Act of Parliament ordayned, that King <hi>Philip</hi> ſhould be Protector of her iſſue, and Gouernour of the Realmes, vntill their Prince or Princeſſes ſhould come of able yeares.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 2. and 2. <hi>Philip</hi> &amp; <hi>Mary.</hi> Enacted that King <hi>Philip</hi> ſhould bee Protector of his ſuppoſed iſſue.</note>
            </p>
            <p>King <hi>Philip</hi> apprehended continuall feares, and doubts of the Engliſh, in regard of the maligners of his marriage: for at his firſt entrance the dore of his great Hall of his Court, for the moſt part kept ſhut, or ſtraightly guarded, not any ſuffered to enter, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe his buſineſſe was firſt made knowne.<note place="margin">Acts and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents. <hi>pag.</hi> 1643. 6. King <hi>Philip</hi> fearefull of the Engliſh. Thoſe Lords that were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the mariage, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to ſend their weapons to the Tower.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Lords ſome of them hauing formerly ſhewed themſelues to haue been much againſt the marriage, hauing leaue to depart <hi>London,</hi> had ſtraight com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement to ſend all their Harneſſe and Artillary to the Tower, which was done. The King was as well doubtfull of thoſe that beare a faire ſhew, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing it vpon this ground: For that a Noble man in conſultation had giuen his counſell to cut off La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Elizabeths</hi> head; whereby he aſſured himſelfe, that thoſe ſo bad minded towards their owne naturall Princeſſe, could not be better to him a ſtranger: hee was graciouſly courteous to the Engliſh, and ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3007:19"/>all wayes and meanes to gaine their loues and affections: For which he layd a good foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, became an earneſt mediator,<note place="margin">King <hi>Philip</hi> a great friend to the Lady <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
               </note> and ſolicited the Queene for the liberty of that innocent Princeſſe her ſiſter the Lady <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who ſtill remained a ſolitary priſoner in <hi>Woodſtock</hi> about <hi>Wyats</hi> conſpiracy, though no proofes could be brought againſt her for any of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Philip</hi> at length obtained his ſuite, that the Lady <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was brought to <hi>Hampton</hi> Court, and for 14. dayes there locked vp, and laid at by <hi>Gardiner</hi> to ſubmit her ſelfe, hauing not ſeene her ſiſter in two yeares before: ſhee was ſent for into the Queenes Chamber about tenne of the clocke in the night, which ſhe no ſooner had entered, but falling vpon her knees, ſhee prayed to God to preſerue her Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Maieſtie, proteſting her loyalty, and truth to her perſon whatſoeuer had beene ſpoken, or inſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the contrary.</p>
            <p>At which time there was betweene them long and much debate, the Lady <hi>Elizabeth</hi> made good her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency: Queene <hi>Mary</hi> replied in Spaniſh (God knowes,) and ſo went away, King <hi>Philip</hi> ſtanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde the Arras all the time.</p>
            <p>About ſome weeke after,<note place="margin">Princeſſe <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi> relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of her im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment.</note> the Princeſſe <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was diſcharged of <hi>Bening field,</hi> whom ſhe termed her laylor, and leaue of liberty, yet ſo that Sir <hi>Thomas Pope</hi> a priuie Councellour, and Maſter <hi>Gage</hi> the Queenes Gentleman Vſher, were ſtill her Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, all Queene <hi>Maries</hi> time.</p>
            <p>But the death of <hi>Gardiner</hi> immediatly followed, thoſe ſtormes grew more calmer, and the Lady <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:3007:19"/>euery day more affectionately reſpected. King <hi>Philip</hi> by this his honourable and worthy act, gayned him the loue of many the Nobility and Gentry of the Kingdome, and did thereby ſo indeare and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratiate himſelfe into the affections of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,<note place="margin">Nota.</note> that they turned their hate and diſtaſte vpon thoſe that had beene the chiefe opponents and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligners of the marriage: So that they are indeede like a ſtreame of water, though turned out of the current, yet will runne.</p>
            <p>Hee euery day gayned more and more vpon the loues of the Engliſh,<note place="margin">King <hi>Philip</hi> gayned the loue of the Engliſh.</note> in his affection gracing and countenancing them, and his owne Country men: he carried himſelfe wonderous euenly, which kept good correſpondencie betweene the two Nations, though his marriage with Queene <hi>Mary</hi> made him Maſter of all here in <hi>England,</hi> yet in his honeſt and iuſt diſpoſition, thoſe Articles which he had formerly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed vnto, alwayes maiſtered his affections obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiouſly, and exactly performing them, which is not alwayes ſeene in Princes; he had the two chiefe orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments belonging to a King, that is to ſay, mercy and Iuſtice, for the one he was both a moderator and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator,<note place="margin">King <hi>Philip</hi> his good diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to Iuſtice.</note> what hee could to reſtraine thoſe ſeuere and cruell perſecutions, committed in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> time: then for Iuſtice he had a Princely inclination to haue it duly adminiſtered. Amongſt many there is one peece of Iuſtice noted in him: an Engliſhman at <hi>London</hi> in ſingle fight being killed by a Spaniard, he was executed, though by the Strangers two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Duckets were offered for the Spaniard his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue, which could not ſtay the hand of Iuſtice: For
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3007:20"/>that there will be further occaſion hereafter in my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended courſe, for the purſuing of this my relation, I will write here no more of him in his particular (as being not to be doubted) he was no leſſe worthy and graciouſly diſpoſed a Prince, then hee is here briefly diſcribed, or at leaſt howſoeuer if his vertues had not exceeded his imperfections, (which is a great happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to a State where ſuch a King is) by ſome of our Writers that haue written of thoſe times, we ſhould haue heard of him at large.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Philip</hi> fruſtrate of his hope for his heire, vpon the fourth of September 1555. tooke ſhipping, and went to viſite his Father the Emperour, and to take poſſeſſion of the Low Countries, where he ſtayed a yeare and a halfe, to the great griefe of Queene <hi>Mary</hi> his wife. But returning, came to <hi>Douer,</hi> hee was by the Queene met on the way, and brought through <hi>London,</hi> accompanied with many Peeres of the Realme, as in triumph againſt a Coronation.</p>
            <p>In the Kings abſence many conſpiracies had beene attempted, but they were like vapours that are drawne vp by the Sunne, and falls againe: ſo thoſe actors (as commonly incident to ſuch men) were drawne vp with hemp by the hand of Iuſtice, before they did any hurt,<note place="margin">Hollinſh. Grafton.</note> the perſons and perticular paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, I alſo leaue to thoſe Authors before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>The Emperour ouer-worne with the affaires of the world,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Grimſton</hi> in his French. Hiſtory.</note> and wearied with the troubles of turmoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling warres, or rather touched with remorſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, for the infinite miſeries brought by him vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Florence, Naples, Scicilie, Tuſcane, Elbe,</hi> and <hi>Calabria,</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:3007:20"/>perſwaded that thoſe mournefull iarres of Chriſtian Princes,<note place="margin">Nota.</note> had giuen to the Turke aduantage vpon di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers parts of <hi>Europe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iarres of Chriſtian Princes gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to the Turke.</note> he called his ſonne King <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>England</hi> vnto <hi>Bruxels</hi> (as is ſaid) where by authentick Letters, reſigned all his Realmes vnto him, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all his Eſtates, and Subiects to acknowledge and hold him their lawfull King, and among many other inſtructions, and moſt wiſe exhortations, gaue him charge chiefly to hold amity with the French, leaſt otherwiſe the warres of thoſe puiſant Nations might oppreſſe all Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charles</hi> the Emperour, as he hath beene diſcribed, by thoſe that haue written his life, hee was an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent wiſe Prince, which is ſhewed both in that his ſage and graue obſeruation, as alſo for his like Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell giuen to his ſonne <hi>Philip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The conſideration of both are fitting,<note place="margin">Nota.</note> and ſutable for theſe our now times; as firſt the infinite miſerable calamities that thoſe Countries of <hi>Germany</hi> haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured, and may be brought vnto by the late Warres there, and may giue much aduantage for the Turke againſt Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p>The other in likelihood, it may be a great happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for a State to be in league, and amity with a neighbour Nation, that is opulent and powerfull, and to haue it confirmed and faſtened by marriage,<note place="margin">Nota.</note> which commonly is then inuiolable: There might be much written vpon this Subiect, but I will leaue it to thoſe of better ability to doe it, onely as I paſſed by I haue called.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Philip</hi> was much enclined to peace, and Queene <hi>Mary</hi> his wife at that time much more, both
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3007:21"/>to hold him with her at home, and to ſupport the Religion which ſhee had againe raiſed by reſtoring the Clergie to their wonted poſſeſſions,<note place="margin">The Nobility would not part with the lands they had belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Clergie. The Queene by Parliament all ſuch like lands ſhe had.</note> whereof much was then held in the Noble mens hands, from whoſe hard hold hardly could any thing be wreſted: But thoſe in her owne, ſhee freely reſigned by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with this moſt Chriſtian reſolution &amp; Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaying, that ſhee ſet more by the ſaluation of her owne ſoule, then ſhe did by the reuenewes of all the Kingdomes of the world, and ſo committed the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoration, and diſpoſe thereof vnto the Pope, and Cardinall <hi>poole</hi> his Legate, to the great enritching of the Church, and impoueriſhing of the Crowne.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Philip</hi> following his Fathers aduice, made peace with <hi>Fraunce,</hi> which was to continue for fiue yeares,<note place="margin">The Pope be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged, confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned within the walls of <hi>Rome. John Slcidon.</hi>
               </note> which no ſooner was made, then againe was broken: one principall occaſion was miniſtred, by Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the fourth, then an Enemy to the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, whom Duke <hi>Alua</hi> had beſieged, and confined him within the walls of <hi>Rome,</hi> hee ſent to <hi>Henry</hi> the French king for ayde, and withall ſent him a tryum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant Hat, with a ſtately Sword, and thereupon had ſuccour by the <hi>Guiſe,</hi> who remoued the ſiege, and ſet the Pope at liberty. But the French decreaſing for want of pay, and the Spaniard ſtill raiſing their Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phees of victory, the Pope thought it the ſureſt to hold with the ſtrongeſt,<note place="margin">The Pope tooke the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt ſide, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the Spaniard.</note> fell off from the amity of the French King, and was reconciled to the Spaniard: ſo that by this occaſion there grew a ſtrong party a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King of <hi>Fraunce:</hi> For by King <hi>Philip</hi> and Queene <hi>Mary</hi> his wife, he had both <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> againſt him, and the Pope, no leſſe powerfull there,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3007:21"/>then he was, within the walls of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The occaſion that Queene <hi>Mary</hi> tooke for the breach of the peace, was more vpon pretences,<note place="margin">Iohn Stowes <hi>Annalls.</hi>
               </note> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and pickt quarrels, then any iuſt cauſe mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred by the French King. Queene <hi>Mary</hi> ſent him a defiance, and inſtantly proclaymed warres againſt <hi>Fraunce.</hi> And King <hi>Philip</hi> her husband went in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for the proſecuting thereof. The Queene imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly ſent after the King her husband, the Earle of <hi>Pembroke</hi> Generall, Viſcount <hi>Mountacute,</hi> with diuers Earles and Barons, with a great Army, who came to King <hi>Philip,</hi> and ioyned with him, whilſt the Duke of <hi>Sau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, Brunſwike;</hi> the Earles of <hi>Egmonde, Horne,</hi> and <hi>Mansfield,</hi> inuaded the French confines, and planted a ſtrong ſiege againſt Saint <hi>Quintens,</hi> which ſhortly after by the Engliſh,<note place="margin">St. <hi>Quintens</hi> wonne by the Engliſh.</note> was nobly and victoriouſly wonne to the great loſſe, and diſcomfort of the French, <hi>Monſieur Mountomorancie</hi> Conſtable of <hi>Frunce,</hi> and Generall, was taken priſoner.</p>
            <p>Queene <hi>Mary</hi> contrary to her promiſe and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, made vpon her marriage with King <hi>Philip,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled her Subiects, with the quarrels of the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards: The greatioy conceiued for the victory, was ſhortly after daſhed, with as much ſorrow for the loſſe of <hi>Galice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Engliſh after they had ſo gotten Saint <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens,</hi> they afforded to themſelues either little liſt, or leaſure more, or otherwiſe; but betooke themſelues to their delights, diſorders, and pleaſures, and onely to keepe, and make good what they had newly got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, grew negligent, and careleſſe of the Towne of <hi>Calice,</hi> that the Forts thereabouts for defence being
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3007:22"/>vnreſpectiuely regarded (wonne by that victorious Prince <hi>Edward</hi> the third) and that by no leſſe then eleuen moneths ſiege (were in the compaſſe of eight dayes beſieged, ſurprized, and wonne) in the depth of Winter, to the worldes wonder, and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great ſuſpition of treachery, which happened the the 12. day of lanuary: and in the ſecond moneth, were ſurrendred the ſtrong Fort of <hi>Guies,</hi> and <hi>Hames,</hi> whereby all the Engliſh ſooting was loſt in the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent of <hi>Fraunce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So here you may ſee, that our owne Writers af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that the breach of the peace with the French King, was not any wayes by the occaſion of King <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip,</hi> nor the loſſe of <hi>Calice</hi> by his default: After his great victory at Saint <hi>Quintens,</hi> he would admit no peace at all with the French, but with reſtoring <hi>Calice,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the Engliſh themſelues, without him made their peace, and renownced <hi>Calice</hi> to the French for euer.</p>
            <p>Theſe Ioſſes were greeuous, to the Engliſh Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and moſt of all, to Queene <hi>Mary</hi> her ſelfe: After ſhe had aboliſhed the Goſpell, reſtored the Popes Supremacie, whatſoeuer ſhe tooke in hand, was no wayes proſperous, but in all things infortunate: her conceptions failing, extreame dearthes rayning, hurt done by thunders from heauen, and Fire in the Royall Nauy, Forraigne loſſes, <hi>Calice</hi> ſurrendred, which could neuer be recouered, vpon any compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition; and King <hi>Philip</hi> alwayes in troubles, and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moyling warres, occaſioned his keeping from court, ſo that Queene <hi>Mary</hi> her life (during her raignet) was little pleaſurable, or that ſhe ſcance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ioyed any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, or at leaſe little contentment as all: which ſo
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3007:22"/>much augmented hor melancholly, which grew to a burning Feauer, when ſhe had raigned fiue yeares;<note place="margin">Queene <hi>Mary</hi> with griefe died.</note> ſhe ended her life at her Mannour of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iames,</hi> and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth interred amongſt her Aunceſtors in the Abby of <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now next in courſe doth follow, the relation of the paſſages, betweene <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spaine:</hi> after King <hi>Philip</hi> his returne thither, which was immediatly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Queene <hi>Maries</hi> death, and during the time of the raigne, of the late Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> where then I come to the Spring head, from whence the auerſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and vnwillingneſſe of the Commons doe riſe, for our Princes Royall match with <hi>Spaine,</hi> the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the late Hoſtile warrs, with other the paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which plebian like, they haue by tradition, as the Brittaines had the ſtory of their times deliuered them by their <hi>Druides.</hi> Theſe things, being they concerne the breach of the league betweene <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> may be thought too deepe, and of too great a conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of State, to be medled withall: I hope I ſhall miniſter no cauſe of offence, nor innouation, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther giue ſatisfaction, and occaſion moderation: For here I obſerue in the Country, the Papiſts in their diſcourſes, magnifying the Royall proceedings of King <hi>Philip,</hi> and the Spaniards in generall, lay ſome taxe, and aſperſion vpon the late Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> which is very harſh, and much diſpleaſing to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants: And then on the other ſide, they vrge and agrauate againſt the Spaniards, with much bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and thereupon they fall into expoſtulation, <hi>Pro &amp; Gon,</hi> of the Princes match, neither vnderſtanding nor taking into their conſiderations, more or farther,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3007:23"/>then to make good their owne part, &amp; conceit, which breedeth difference amongſt our ſelues, maketh and maintaineth a partition wall, betwixt the Engliſh and the Spaniards, in ſuch loue as ſhould be betwixt Subiects, whoſe Soueraignes are in league &amp; amity. That the Commons might not ſo diſobediently, in their affections, muteny againſt that which the King hath ſo laboured, and doth ſo much deſire to bring to paſſe, as alſo for their ſo much expoſtulation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the ſcope of my endeuours, onely end, and ayme of my ambition is, that theſe my labours might oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion ſome moderation therein: For the better ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhing thereof, and giuing the better ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in thoſe particulars, I will here relate ſome ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruations, which the Papiſts haue formerly colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and vſually in their diſcourſes will vrge them: the vſage and carriage of the Spaniards towards the Engliſh, and other Nations, and the Engliſh to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, with ſome other former paſſages be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the two Nations. I could wiſh the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons would beleeue theſe things, ſo farre forth as their owne knowledge, or true informations doe not extend the contrary, and the Papiſts to doe the like; for that which is here alleaged either concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the late Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> or the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> neither part to be tranſported with paſſion; but of thoſe things, to make a fauourable, and the beſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and mutually to take them into a charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and reconciliable conſideration: The particulars are as followeth.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts alleage,<note place="margin">The Papiſts collections.</note> that King <hi>Phillip</hi> had a great deſire to continue in league, and amity with <hi>England,</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:3007:23"/>and that after he returned into <hi>Spaine,</hi> conſtantly maintained the ſame for thirty yeares together, would neuer hearken to giue aſſiſtance to any the diſcontented Engliſh Nobility, that would haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled; and in the yeare 1568. abſolutely denyed aide to the Earles of <hi>Northumberland</hi> and <hi>Weſtmerland,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Dacres,</hi> when they roſe vp in rebellion, in the North parts of England, how the King after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, to wit, in the yeare 1575, for contenting her Maieſty at the Perſwaſion of ſome of his own Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, but namely the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendador Maior, that forthe preſent gouerned Flaunders, was content to yeeld to the baniſhment of all Engliſh Papiſts, out of his eſtate in <hi>Flaunders</hi> for the ſpace of two years, though he paid them alwaies their penſions to liue on, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. And for the ſame conſideration of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with the Queene, and for keeping his league, he denied diuers yeares help to the Iriſh, that deſired the ſame, as namely in the yeare 1578. to Sir <hi>Iames Fitz-Morris,</hi> and Sir <hi>Thomas Stukely,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Siukley</hi> ſlaine.</note> and to the later of them, when afterwards he with ſome 5. or. 600. men that he brought from <hi>Italy,</hi> the King would not grant ſo much as a port in <hi>Spain,</hi> to enter into; wherby he was forced to paſſe to <hi>Lisborne,</hi> where finding the King of <hi>Poxtugall</hi> ready to goe with his Army to <hi>Barbarie,</hi> he could not refuſe to goe with him, was there ſlaine.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Iames Fitz-Morris</hi> returning againe the next yeare, to aske ſuccours for the Iriſh, to haue from <hi>Spaine</hi> ſome forces, to carie for <hi>Ireland,</hi> denied the ſame againe, vntill at the laſt, at the carneſt ſuite of the Pope, for that Doctor <hi>Saunders</hi> vpon his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame zeale, had aduentured to goe thither before
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3007:24"/>in perſon, to comfort the Iriſh, not hauing with him aboue 50. men, the King was contented to winke at, and ſay nothing, whiles <hi>Sega</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Placentia,</hi> the Popes <hi>Nuncio,</hi> vnder certaine of the Italian Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, did ſend thither ſome fiue hundred Souldiers, taken vpon the Sea coaſts of <hi>Italy,</hi> which were thoſe that were ſlaine by the Lord <hi>Gray</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then doe the Papiſts farther vrge, the Queenes ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>Fluſhing, Brill,</hi> and <hi>Oſte-end,</hi> and other Townes in <hi>Flaunders,</hi> and likewiſe the aſſiſting, and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing of Duke <hi>Mathias,</hi> at his firſt comming, and after <hi>Monſicur</hi> Duke of <hi>Alenſon;</hi> and likewiſe the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vp the title of <hi>Don Antonio</hi> King of <hi>Portugale:</hi> and ſending him into his Country, with an Army: The intercepting the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> his money, firſt in the Duke of <hi>Alua</hi> his time, and many times afterwards, the ſending of <hi>Hawkins, Frobriſher, Drake,</hi> and <hi>Candiſh,</hi> and others to the <hi>Indies,</hi> and ſome of them euen to <hi>Spaine</hi> it ſelfe: For which there were ſpeciall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions graunted, that whatſoeuer could be taken from the Spaniards, to be held as lawfull repriſalls, and thoſe Commiſſions to be ſpecified, in <hi>Stowe</hi> his Chronicles.</p>
            <p>Then they alleadge,<note place="margin">The breach of the peace between <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> &amp; <hi>Spaine.</hi>
               </note> that the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> did thereupon make arreſts of the Engliſh ſhips, then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly grew enmity, and oepn warres: and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, <hi>viz.</hi> in the yeare 1588. the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> with his great Fleete, attempted the inuaſion of <hi>England,</hi> which yet with many the Engliſh, is too freſh in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts farther vrge, and haue collected, that in Nouember 1591. Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> publiſhed a
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3007:24"/>ſtrict Proclamation for ſearching out, apprehending and puniſhing of Seminaries and Ieſuites, and ſuch as receiued and fauoured them in <hi>England,</hi> ſharpe &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere lawes, made and executed vpon them, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther both to put feares and doubts into the heads of the Commons, as alſo to exaſperate them againſt the Spaniards; Farther vrging, that the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> his great power, forces, and wealth, were dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to <hi>England,</hi> poſſeſſing more Crownes, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and countries, then euer any Chriſtian Prince had before, and yet ambitiouſly ſeeketh more, endeauouring to make himſelfe abſolute Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch of the world, and that his cariage towards o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Princes and their ſubiects was tyrannous, and thoſe nations which he ſubdued, were cruelly dealt withall, and kept in great ſlauery.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts for all theſe particulars, hane collected appologicall defences, which in their arguments and diſcourſes, they will much inſiſt vpon, to the high commendations of the Kings of <hi>Spaine,</hi> their royall and gratious proceedings with other Princes, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their ſubiects, as alſo with their owne, which are as followeth.</p>
            <p>Firſt, they propoſe and recommend it to conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; For the conceaued opinion amongſt the Engliſh, that the Kings of <hi>Spaine,</hi> their gouernment is ſtrict, or rather indeed ſomewhat cruell, the maine occaſion thereof is. The countries, dominions, and territories, are very large and ſpacious, many of them atchieued by conqueſt, formerly gouerned by <hi>Roitelets</hi> as petty Kings, and now inhabited by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall nations, of ſeuerall natures; So that the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3007:25"/>neceſſitie, and diſpoſition of the Kings of <hi>Spaine</hi> their affaires requireth; that they muſt carry ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what a harder hand in their gouernment, then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie, otherwiſe they cannot ſecure, nor make good their plantations, nor retaine their ſubiects in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. And the very name of conqueſt, imports vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence and miſery, and is of ſo harſh a ſound, and odious in nature, that from a Nation ſubdued, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractions will ſuppreſſe all commendations a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour ſhall any waies deſerue; Though their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerning of ſuch like ſubiects may be particuler, yet the aſperſion in that kinde will runne in the generall, and a long time (as it were) in diſcent, eſpecially a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt malignant diſpoſitions.</p>
            <p>In remote parts of Kings Dominions where the gouernment by them is committed to ſubordinate Officers, &amp; Commanders, ſometimes barbarous and in humane acts, may be done by them, &amp; the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon people, which Kings in their nature may much ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre and deteſt, yet for the ſame in their honour and reputation they often ſuffer.</p>
            <p>Then they further alleage, that the Kings of <hi>Spaine</hi> to the Turkes, Moores, and ſuch like Infidels, haue beene many times a ſcourge. But then in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, with the Italians, Portugals, French, Engliſh, Scottiſh, and Flemmiſh, their dealings with them, to haue beene moſt honourable, quiet, iuſt, and without iniurie offered to any, which is ſaid to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, by their owne teſtimonies and witneſſes, alſo of many Writers.</p>
            <p>For the warre,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Thillip</hi> the ſecond.</note> and other affaires, that haue paſſed in <hi>Portugall,</hi> they were ſo carried and no otherwiſe,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3007:25"/>for the iuſtification thereof, out of <hi>Hieromme Francht a Genoes</hi> that was preſent, and wrot the ſtorie, and in other points ſheweth himſelf no great friend to Spaniards; yet doth he ſo iuſtifie all the Kings acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in theſe affaires, euen by the teſtimonie of the Portugals themſelues, as they ſeeme rather ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrupulous then onely iuſtifiable.</p>
            <p>Then there is further cyted <hi>Genebrard</hi> a French Writer, that ſetteth out the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble proceedings with <hi>France,</hi> in all the times of the minorities of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond his children, to wit, <hi>Francis, Charles</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> the third, and how he neuer ſought, either to profit himſelfe, or to impaire the kingdome of <hi>France</hi> during thoſe troubles, and thereupon giueth a touch by way of taxe, for the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>Newhauen</hi> by the Engliſh; further alleaging, that the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> at his owne charges, ſent aides of men, horſe, victuals, and money often times to the ſuccours of thoſe young Princes, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the old enmities and emulation, betweene thoſe two Crownes of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> and the cruell warres that had paſſed betweene them many yeares. And maketh further relation of the king his clement proceeding with his owne ſubiects, that rebelled in the low Countries, as appeared by his many par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons, peaces, and tollerations made with them: his liberall and noble dealings with the Engliſh, Iriſh, and Scottiſh, eſpecially ſuch as were ſubiect to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, for their conſcience at home, thoſe he ſuſtained liberally, without requiring any ſeruice at their hands.</p>
            <p>And laſtly for the great wealth, forces, ſtrength,<note place="margin">Note.</note>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:3007:26"/>and power of the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> being a friend, and temperately vſed, cannot be fearefull to any good man but rather comfortable; nor to be dangerous to Chriſtendome, but rather a great and ſinguler ſtay, and prouidence of Almighty God (who foreſeeing the tumults and reuolts) that hereſies might bring in and the dangers Chriſtendome might be ſubiect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, by the great power and ſtrength of Infidels, the Turkes and Moores hath prouided ſo potent, and opulent a Prince as the king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> for the defence of the Catholike Church.</p>
            <p>For the manifeſtation thereof, two ſpeciall obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations worthy of note haue beene collected, and cited, the firſt after that interleaged and indiſſolua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble knot of amity and alyance which was betweene <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeauenth, <hi>Ferdinando</hi> and <hi>Iſabella,</hi> King and Queene of <hi>Spaine,</hi> there mutually paſſed betweene them, many Letters congratulatory, amongſt which, there came Letters from <hi>Ferdinande</hi> and <hi>Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bella,</hi> ſignifying the finall conqueſt of <hi>Granada</hi> from the Moores, which action it ſelfe ſo worthy, King <hi>Ferdinando</hi> (whoſe manner was) as indeed the nature is, neuer to loſe any vertue for the ſhewing) expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and diſplayed in his Leters at large, all the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularities, and religious punctures and ceremonies, that were obſerued in the reception of the Citie and king dome; ſhewing amongſt other things, that the King would not by any meanes in perſon enter the City, vntill he had firſt alooſe ſeene the Croſſe ſet vp vpon the greater Tower of <hi>Granada,</hi> whereby it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Chriſtian ground: That likewiſe, before lie would enter, he did homage to God alone, pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3007:26"/>by an Herauld from the height of that Tower, that he did acknowledge to haue recouered that kingdome by the helpe of God Almighty, and the glorious Virgin, and the vertuous Apoſtle S. <hi>Iames,</hi> and the holy Father Pope <hi>Inocent</hi> the eight, together with the aides and ſeruice of his Prelates, Nobles, and Commons; that he ſtirred not from the campe, till he had ſeene a little armie of Martyrs, to the number of ſeauen hundred and more Chriſtians (that had liued in bonds and ſeruitude as ſlaues to the Moores) paſſe before his eies, ſinging a pſalme for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, and that he had giuen tribute to God by almes and reliefe, extended to them all, for his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion into the City: theſe things were in the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, with many more ceremonies of a kinde of holy oſtentation.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Henry</hi> euer willing to put himſelfe into the conſort, or quier of religious actions, and natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affecting much the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> (as much as one King could affect another, partly for his vertues, and partly for a counterpoiſe to <hi>France</hi> vpon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of theſe Letters, ſent all his Nobles and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats, that were about the court, together with the Maior and Aldermen of <hi>London</hi> in great ſolemnity to the Church of <hi>Pauls,</hi> there to heare a declaration from Biſhop <hi>Morton,</hi> then Lord Chancellour and Cardinall, ſtanding vpon the vppermoſt ſtep, or halfe pace before the Quier; and all the Nobles, Prelats, and Gouernours of the Citie at the foot of the ſtayres, made a ſpeech vnto them, letting them know that they were aſſembled in that conſecrated place, to ſing vnto God a new ſong; for that (ſaid he) theſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3007:27"/>many yeares the Chriſtians haue not gained new ground, or territorie vpon the infidels, nor enlarged and ſet further the bounds of the chriſtian world: But this is now done by the proneneſſe &amp; deuotion of <hi>Feredinando</hi> and <hi>Iſabella,</hi> King and Queene of <hi>Spaine,</hi> who haue (to their immortall honour) reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered the great and rich kingdome of <hi>Granada,</hi> and the populous and mighty citie of the ſame name, from the Moores, hauing beene in poſſeſſion thereof by the ſpace of ſeauen hundred yeares and more: For which, this aſſembly and all Chriſtians are to render laud and thankes to God, and to celebrate this noble act of the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> who in this is not onely victorious, but Apoſtolicall in the gaining of new Prouinces to the Chriſtian Faith; and the rather, for that this victory and conqueſt is obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, without much effuſion of bloud, whereby it is to bohoped, that there ſhall be gained, not onely new territories, but infinite ſoules to the Church of Chriſt, whom the Almighty (as it ſeemes) would haue to be conuerted. Herewithall, he did relate ſome of the moſt memorable particulers of the warre and victorie; and after his ſpeech ended, the whole aſſembly went ſolemnly in proceſſion, and <hi>Te Deum</hi> was ſung.</p>
            <p>Then for the other particuler obſeruation I colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and cited, was in the raigne of <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> here formerly treated of. And about the 14. yeare of the late Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the Turke hauing conquered many Ilands, and Cities, borde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vpon the Seas, and in the yeare 1571. knowing deuiſion among diuers Chriſtian Princes, as well for
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3007:27"/>matters of Religion, as affaires of State, vpon hope of which aduantage, he aſſembled a great Army of Gallies, preſuming thereby to make himſelfe Maſter of the Sea, and Lord of the Land; they were encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred by the Chriſtians:<note place="margin">The battell of <hi>Lepanto.</hi>
               </note> For the which <hi>Don Iohn de Auſtria,</hi> a braue Commaunder, was ſent by the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> with a great Fleete of Ships, Gallies, and Galliaſſes; ſo that at one inſtant there were ſunke and taken 230. of the Turkiſh Gallies, and 30000. Mahamotiſts ſlaine, beſides many taken priſoners. There were 12000. Chriſtians redeemed from Turk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh ſlauery, and 8000. ſlaine; with the loſſe of leauen or eight Gallies: Our Writers affirme,<note place="margin">Stowe.</note> that the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Fleete, was a mayne occaſion of that memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble victory, and that the Galliaſſes did admirable ſeruice in that expedition.</p>
            <p>Loe here you ſee the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> his commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation by the Papiſts, extended to the height; with ſome taxe of the late Queene <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> wherein I haue beene ſparing in my relation, to that they will ſpeake in ſome bitterneſſe, they doe therein but as men that throwe duſt againſt the winde. Her Royall worth is left behinde recorded, farre more durable, then in Letters of Br4aſſe, a Princeſſe of bleſſed fame, and euerlaſting memory: to write of her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, any thing neere in proportion to her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing, it is a worke for excellent Writers. They may in that faculty excell, but vpon that ſubiect ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer exceede; therefore for my particuler, I will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, and conclude both together, ſhe had euery way as many vertues as could liue, and more then could dye. I doe not here reuine, nor make repetition of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3007:28"/>theſe things, to giue farther occaſion of faction; but rather for the preſent moderate, and in the end ſome way reconcile, and reclaime the diſaffections of the common people, preſuming they will produce no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther effects, as when the Country people, eſpecially thoſe affected to Papiſtry, ſhall vnderſtand, and take into their conſiderations, former paſſages, and then being not ſo peremptory, and confident, as now they are to croſſe, greeue, and agrauate againſt thoſe (that in reſpect of religion) in their affections, haue beene ſomewhat vnwilling for our Princes Royall match: I preſume it cannot but rather farther moderation and community, then otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts did not obſerue, or at leaſt doe not deſire it ſhould, that though the King of <hi>Spame</hi> did often denie to afford ſuccours to the Iriſh Rebels: yet at the laſt (as by their owne collections appeare) did winke and ſay nothing, when Doctor <hi>Saunders</hi> and <hi>Sega,</hi> the one going ouer into <hi>Ireland</hi> in perſon, the other ſending forces thither: ſo that Queene <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> her ſuccouring thoſe in <hi>Flaunders,</hi> which the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> held Rebels, ſhe did no more then he did, but onely the difference was, ſhe wont roundly and reſolutely on, and the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> ſomewhat reſerued, and priuately: And the monies taken from Duke <hi>Alua,</hi> and other rich prizes brought in, by <hi>Haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins, Frobiſher, Drake,</hi> and <hi>Cauendiſh,</hi> they were onely to pay the Souldiers. Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was of ſuch a gracious &amp; Royall diſpoſition, ſhe could not endure but to haue her Souldiers payde the money ſhould haue payde Duke <hi>Alua</hi> his Souldiers: but it payde them that fought againſt him, ſo that it was but miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imployed.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:3007:28"/>
            <p> The king of <hi>Spaine</hi> doubtleſſe was deſirous to haue continued his league with <hi>England,</hi> whereof he made many good demonſtrations: therefore I could wiſh hee ſhould not looſe his due commendation in that particular: But it ſeemed hee preſumed on Queene <hi>Elizabeths</hi> patience, that for ſuffering, as it were, but a handfull of Souldiers of his Subiects, to goe for <hi>Ireland,</hi> to aſſiſt the Rebels there, thought ſo ſmall an occaſion, would not haue broken the league: But it ſeemes peace long before, was laide vp, that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a dry commodity, ſo that it ſoone tooke fire.</p>
            <p>Then for the Proclamation, vrged againſt Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> publiſhed in Nouember 1591. with the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere lawes then made, and executed againſt the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts: they were alwayes plotting, conſpiring, and attempting, the taking away her life; thoſe lawes were but like a good and skilfull Phiſician, that drew ſome bloud, to preſerue much more, the life of our Soueraigne, and indeede the life and light of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell. Tyrants ſhed bloud for pleaſure, Princes for neceſſity. Let the proceedings of her predeceſſor, be put into the other balance, there will bee found great difference: Wherefore it is beſt for all parties, either wayes affected, to let theſe things alone vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiued, neither weighed, nor farther diſcourſed of.</p>
            <p>I will here (vnder ſauour) preſume to adde ſome obſeruations, which may ſome way moderate the diſaffections of the common people towards the Spaniards, concerning thoſe particular paſſages be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned.</p>
            <p>The Pope you ſee was Author, though hee made the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> Actor, for the breach of the peace,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:3007:29"/>as being too much led by the Pope, which was no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary thing. Let vs but reade our Engliſh Chronicles, wee ſhall there finde, that many of our moſt puiſſant and victorious Kings here in <hi>England,</hi> their powers and prerogatiues haue beene captiua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Pope, and ſome by them brought to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely ends, alwayes working vpon them, and the indiſpoſition of the times, where they ſaw, either a weake Prince, a factious Nobility, or a mutinous Commons; by their directions, their Legates and Clergie would be alwayes working, to make the Pope and themſelues maiſters both of the King and Kingdome. If they would teach Kings truly the wayes of righteouſneſſe, let God alone with his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, &amp; Princes with their inheritances: not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe and direct ſtratagems, nor be ſo violent whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they get dominion to ſuppreſſe the Proteſtant Religion, and aduance the Romane Catholique, it would bhee a moſt bleſſed happineſſe to all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>Then laſtly, the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> his attempt in 88. was by the Popes inſtigation, &amp; had no doubt his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nediction, for aſſurance of good ſucceſſe therein: but it had a contrary effect, brought a malediction, and an infauſting vpon him, and his King dome, as an ill Prognoſtick, which in the euent proued true. The Spaniards haue no cauſe to ioy at the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance thereof; the Engliſh onely to thanke God for their deliuerance. If the Spaniards will forget and paſſe it ouer (as being farre the greater looſers) it is both charity and religion, for the Engliſh to doe the like. And the rather for that, and ſuch like hoſtile
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3007:29"/>actions, paſſing betweene the two Nations in the time of warre: and now in peace, in all Chriſtian and religious conſiderations, enuie, and hatred, ſhould haue an end, and not be continued. States are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the wheele; times haue their turnings, and great Princes themſelues not free from calumny and detraction, and many times with much agra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation therein.</p>
            <p>For theſe particulars I will conclude, with that graue and ſage obſeruation, of <hi>Cornelius Tacitus,</hi> that free tongued Romane, that wrote, they made it a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, to make Kings the inſtruments of oppreſſion; they may many times ſeeme ſo, and yet they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeues of a moſt gracious and Royall diſpoſition. Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> therein not ſecond to any, and yet according to the fate, and faſhion of great princes, by ſome great and graue Councellours neere about her, and by ſome that could thriue onely by warre; ſhe was much ſwayed and ruled, which ſhe thought was no diminution to her commendation, though it made not ſo much for her abſolutenes, yet it ſeemed ſhe held it the more for her ſafety.</p>
            <p>Let vs not be tranſported with paſſion and doubts, beyond reaſon, good ground, or probability; the Kings and Monarchies of <hi>England,</hi> in their whole choiſe of wiues made from all parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> were neuer more fortunate, and happy in any, then in thoſe Royall Queenes, which they had from <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt in this Scene of honour, ſhall be the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Queene <hi>Elenor,</hi> wife to <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt formerly mentioned: what was ſhee but the wonder and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle of her Sex?</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:3007:30"/>
            <p> The next, Queene <hi>Katherine,</hi> wife firſt to Prince <hi>Arthur,</hi> afterwards to <hi>Henry</hi> the eight; ſhee was the cleare mirrour, and example of wiſedome, integrity, ſanctity, and all Royall and Princely vertues; in all which ſhe was farre more precious and excellent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo tryed as ſhe was, with the touchſtone of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſtancia, Izabella, Beringaria,</hi> and <hi>Ioanna,</hi> Spaniſh Princes, all theſe were proper, and peculiar to our Engliſh Monarchy: our owne Chronicles telleth vs no otherwiſe of them, but that they were, as ſo many glorious and conſpicuous lights of matrimoniall faith, loue, piety, and chaſtity.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, King <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond, that married Queene <hi>Mary,</hi> our own Writers leaues him to poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, highly commended. So that for thoſe Princes; that we haue formerly had from <hi>Spaine; England</hi> hath had ioy, and comfort of them; we haue loued them, and they vs.</p>
            <p>Wherefore ſhould we now ſo much doubt, and feare, for the future, the like ſucceſſe? vnleſſe we will conclude, our diſpoſitions are growne worſe, and that the then times deſerued a great part of their commendations: So that here you may ſee, that no Nations in former times, did euer more faithfully and entirely loue each another, or were in more ſtraighter leagues, and bonds of friendſhip vnited to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, then the Engliſh and Spaniards, vntill by the late warre they were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>oynted.</p>
            <p>Seuere iudgement threatens high places.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sa. ca.</hi> 6.4.8.</note> The greateſt happineſſe of great Kings and Princes, is to make happy their Subiects; and that happineſſe on
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:3007:30"/>eath, is eſteemed greateſt, which commeth neereſt to that in heanen, conſiſting onely in the eternity of bleſſed peace: then conſequently thoſe Princes muſt be deemed moſt bleſſed, who doe chiefly direct their Royall cares, and endeuours to bring glory to God on high, peace and good will to thoſe on earth. Our now gracious King hath ſo gouerned vs this 21. yeares, that we haue enioyed that happineſſe, as God hath beene truly honoured, he obayed, and we haue liued in quiet vnder our own Figge trees, and Vines, eating the fruites of our owne labour4s free, from thoſe calamities and miſeries of warre, ſome of our neighbour Nations are ſubiect vnto; and by Gods grace he will ſo continue vs, whereby he will be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily held in the eſteeme, and deemed one of the moſt bleſſed Princes, according to the poſition be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned.</p>
            <p>How willing, deſirous, and obſeruant the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards haue beene, to bee in peace and amity with vs, let the Reader but duly conſider, that which hath beene formerly related, and for farther ſatisfaction, to an ocular experience we late had thereof.<note place="margin">The Xing of <hi>Spaine</hi> his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be in league and amity with <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> No ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner then our now gracious Soueraigne, came to the Crowne, but the King of <hi>Spaine, Philip</hi> the third, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly ſent ouer his Ambaſſadours, ſought peace at his hands, and had it, which euer ſince hath beene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly, nobly &amp; muioable kept, and ſo continued his ſonne now King of <hi>Spaine, Philip</hi> the fourth.</p>
            <p>An ouerture of marriage long time in treaty for our now Royall Prince <hi>Charles,</hi> with the Lady <hi>Maria,</hi> daughter of the ſaid <hi>Philip</hi> the third, by him much deſired, and now as much as her brother <hi>Philip</hi> the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:3007:31"/>fourth, (as it is generally conceiued) that thoſe two Royall Scepters, ſhould be now conioyned in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred knot, and bond of marriage, thereby to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then their auncient Alliances, and make a perpetuall league, and indiſſoluble confederation of bleſſed peace and friendſhip betwixt them.</p>
            <p>Seeing many excellent learned men, meerely out of zeale, and ſome others wiſe and polliticke in the affaires of State, that are true louers of their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, haue written and ſpoken freely, propoſing doubts, feares, and dangers that may come and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue to <hi>England</hi> with the mariage with <hi>Spaine,</hi> and alſo others of both thoſe ſorts of like ranke and quality (only in religion contrarily affected) haue written, and will ſpeake as much, for the approbation and commendation thereof, propoſing the infinite &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable good, the match may be to the Kingdome of <hi>England.</hi> Without farther intermedling, I will leaue thoſe things to their learnings, and iudiciall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences: that which I relate, may be as materials for them to worke on, and is intended but as home made ſtuffe for the Country people, who in State affaires ſees no farther then the <hi>Rhine,</hi> and many of them wade not ſo deepe, as into the point of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet in their affections haue beene very auerſe, and expreſſed vnwillingneſſe, for our Princes Royall match: I would herewithall cloathe, or at leaſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way couer their bare opinions, that there is no ſuch great cauſe of feares, doubts, and dangers, as they ſeeme to apprehend, though the Spaniards were lately our enemies, yet aunciently they were our friends, and ſeeme to deſire to be ſo againe, to liue in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:3007:31"/>league and amity with vs: I would gladly ſo mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and reclaime the diſaffections of the common people, that they might forget and remit, all former occaſions conceaued of diſtaſte, and not in their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and diſcourſes, ſo diſobe diently mutinie, and diſpute againſt our Soueraignes high com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and Royall intentions. It is incident for men ſo to doe, of ſome one of the diſpoſitions fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
            <p>A kingdome compoſed of men of diuers hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and diſpoſitions, whereof ſome doe burne in hatred, ſome buſied in ſeditious practiſes, ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted with factions, ſome tranſported with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentions, ſome carried headlong with furie, others to ſaue themſelues from ſome puniſhment they haue formerly deſerued, or elſe hauing intangled, or rather prodigally conſumed then inheritance <hi>(No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vandis quam gerendis rebus aptiores)</hi> rather deſiring factions and diſorders, then to haue affaires of State ſettled, as knowing they can receiue no benefit, by the well ſettling and compoſure thereof, as the ſicke diſreliſheth all meates whatſoeuer: ſo diſtempered diſpoſitions doe all paſſages of State, be they neuer ſo good, and are indeed a kinde of wilde beaſts, that ſometimes brings themſelues into the toyle, occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the vertues and loyalties of ſome good men to be ſuſpected; his Maieſtie highly diſcontented, and the ſubiect thereby infinitely preiudiced.</p>
            <p>Both of the Proteſtants and Papiſts in <hi>England</hi> to many of them, doe perticipate of thoſe imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſuch indeed as are drawne from the Lees of each Religion.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:3007:32"/>
            <p> Firſt for the Papiſts; ſome of them are growne ſo impetuous, vnbounden, and vnlimmited, both in their carriage and diſcourſes, propoſing and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining dangerous and fearefull poſitions, inſolently intimating, what a golden time they now ſhall haue: theſe things doe much grieue, and produce great feares to many, that are truly religious, and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſly affected: let vs not doubt, but that by Gods grace, the Kings wiſedome and integrity, they ſhall freely enioy that happineſſe to haue quietneſſe, and contentment in their courſes of life and conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, vntill their liues end, when many of thoſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts (who in reſpect of their former exploits and practiſes haue beene found very dangerous) ſhall haue a ſtraighter hand carried ouer them then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe.</p>
            <p>Then there are of thoſe, which only in ſeeming, are ſomewhat more then Proteſtants, their farther diſcription would aske a long diſcourſe, which I will omit: More then this, they thinke they haue much knowledge, when indeed it is meere igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and that engenders vehemency, and vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency produceth paſſion: then with true, ſincere, and regular diſcipline, there is no co-operation. His Maieſty hath beene pleaſed to denote them long ſince, in a ſpeech he made, in his higher houſe of Parliament, as ſaying they were a people, that were euer diſcontented with the preſent gouernment, and impatient to ſuffer any ſuperioritie; which maketh their ſectvnable to be ſuffered, in any well gouerned Common-wealth: many of them thinke they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not miſſe the way to heauen, if they be oppoſite to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:3007:32"/>the Pope, and yet in another way will meet the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt in ſuperſtition; they haue ſo much talked, expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulated of our Princes Royall match, and in their diſpoſitions and diſcourſes, mutening ſo much againſt it, occaſioning many to doe the like, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſting and ſeeming to foreknow future euents, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudicating dangers, both for religion, and ſtate pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticke of the kingdome, ſo that they thereby, and that ſort of Papiſts before mentioned, with their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolencie and boldneſſe, haue much preiudiced the Common-wealth, amuzeth the countrie people; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them ſtand as it were at a gaze, ſo ſpending their time; buying &amp; ſelling, &amp; all dealings in the countrie, more then for victuals and clothes, are much out of vſe; great ſcarcitie of money euery where complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of: they finde by wofull experience, that royall Trading and commerce are much decayed, and our money which was wont to be imployed therein, is now conuerted into the baſterd and barren imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Vſury: Lands and Rents fallen, and cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing failed: ſo that the poore in that courſe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſcarce in any haue beene ſet a worke: whereby they haue endured the extremity of hunger, of all extremities the extreameſt. The affaires and paſſages amongſt men, doe not runne ſo ſmooth as they were wont to doe; all cry out want of money: ſome that haue it, ſits as it were abrood thereon; they will not vent nor aduenture it, as ſaying they will firſt ſee, what will become of the world, which is now a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon phraſe: ſome now and then, ſpeaking as they would haue it, as ſaying the world will mend: the reply that follows is; Nay it will be worſe: Yet it
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:3007:33"/>hath pleaſed God, out of his infinite goodneſſe and mercy ſo to deale with vs, (God giue vs grace to be thankfull) that for our enioying the fruits of the earth; the times haue beene very ſeaſonable, and we haue, and are like to enioy them in great plenty. Yet the ſtate and condition we doe, and are like to liue in onely preiudicated, and chiefly by our ſelues oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned, will rather be miſerable then happy: We are falling into the latter dayes, ignorance and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie ſtriues to get the vpper hand.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid that God aboue all men, doth inſpire Kings; and then it is like, he doth and will inſpire great Councellours of State aboue ordinary men; therefore let vs pray vnto God, they may conſult, and debate of the reaſons, worke, and effect the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies.</p>
            <p>I am now come neere the end of my ſtage, though ſome man of better ability (which had beene farre more fitter) to haue vndertaken this work, I am conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent againſt all thoſe good Wiues formerly menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, to haue come from <hi>Spaine,</hi> and all the reaſons that either hath or can be alleaged, that in all likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and probability, the match may be happy and ſucceſſefull for <hi>England;</hi> the obiection will be, <hi>Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pla illuſtrant, ſed non probant;</hi> in thoſe former times, there was a vniformity of Religion, ſo that now the difference therein, is the onely ſtone of offence, and the maine occaſion conceaued of the feares and doubts of dangers may enſue, as well to the Church reformed, as to the polliticke, and ſtate affaires of the kingdome.</p>
            <p>I muſt ingenuouſly confeſſe, my home-bred ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:3007:33"/>did fly with the flocke: I am no Courtier, (of whom there be too many) that vpon the ſhift of euery King or Princes mariage, doe pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with ſome probable proiect of preferment, before all other reſpects or conſiderations whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer. I doe not yet much ioy at the match, nor ſhould ſorrow if it ſhould not be: onely in point of religion, I will pray vnto God, and hope, we may haue cauſe to ioy thereat hereafter; in the meane time I will not further trouble my ſelfe, as being not the dutie of ſubiects, to intermeddle, or buſie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with the actions of their King; neither in their diſpoſitions and diſcourſes, to mutiny againſt the match, if his Maieſtie and our hopefull Prince ſhall be pleaſed to proceed therein: all that we haue to do is only to obey, and pray to God to direct all things for the beſt, relying on his prouidence, the Kings wiſdome and integrity, and without our fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther expoſtulations, to let his Maieſtie and his Councell alone in the buſineſſe. Certainly God will be glorified, and whatſoeuer man doth or ſhall determine, he will diſpoſe; It is ſaid by him Kings raigne, and Princes decree Iuſtice.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 8.15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I haue to my ſelfe both grounded and collected ſome particular conſiderations, which giues me con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence and reall ſatisfaction, that there is no ſuch cauſe of doubts and dangers, for the Proteſtant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, or ſtate polliticke of the kingdome, as is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally feared; Which collections, I will here in my concluſion relate, onely inuiting vnto them my countrie neighbours and friends: and doe therein
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:3007:34"/>according to the faſhion of Feaſters, wiſh their cheere better for their ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>Though the eyes of humane prouidence, cannot ſee beyond that Horizon, as directly to diſcerne fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture contingents; yet can they onely iudge, what ſeemes fit to be done by probabilitie grounded vpon mature conſideration and profound iudgement: therefore let vs not feare nor doubt, but that by Gods infinite goodneſſe and mercy, the Kings great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, iudgement, and integrity for religion, there will be a gracious, royall prouiſion, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation made.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the countrie people there is much feare and doubt conceiued, the Pope in his power and prerogatiue, being ſo predominant bth in <hi>Spaine,</hi> and with other forraine Princes, by them as Stales we may be drawne into that net.</p>
            <p>The King, that doth ſo much inſiſt vpon his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue here in his owne kingdome, that will not admit any dyminution therein; that he ſhould now giue way to haue it ſubiected to ſuch a dangerous ſorraine power; there is no manner of likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood.</p>
            <p>There haue beene many of our Kings of <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholik Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that haue beene at dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with the Pope.</note> that were Roman Catholiques, and other Forraine Princes, yea, and <hi>Spaine</hi> it ſelfe (which I will here make bold to tell them) wearied and tyred out with the inſupportable preſſures of the Pope, haue beene at great difference with him, at mortall enmity and open warre: as namely <hi>Henry</hi> the fift, the Emperour (haning by the Popes inſtigation) banded againſt
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:3007:34"/>his father <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, who aſſociated him in the Empire, and held him priſoner in that diſtreſſe, that he died; touched after with remorſe of this act,<note place="margin">Note.</note> and reproach of the State, for abandoning the rightes of the Empire, leuies ſixtie thouſand foote, and thirty thouſand horſe for <hi>Italy,</hi> conſtrained the Pope and his Colledge to acknowledge the rights of the Empire, in that forme as <hi>Leo</hi> the fourth had done to <hi>Otho</hi> the ſecond; and before that, <hi>Adrian</hi> to <hi>Charlamaine,</hi> according to the decree of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Rome;</hi> and made him take his oath of fidelity betweene his hands, as to the true and lawfull Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour. The Pope, ſo ſoone as <hi>Henry</hi> was departed home, aſſembles a Councell, nullifies his acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement as done by force, and ſhortly after died. The Emperour to make himſelfe the ſtronger a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his ſucceſſors,<note place="margin">Note.</note> enters into aliance with the King of <hi>England,</hi> takes to wiſe <hi>Maude</hi> the daughter to <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, being but fiue yeares of age.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Calixti</hi> the next ſucceeding Pope, at a Councell held at <hi>Remes</hi> by eccleſiaſticall ſentence, cauſed <hi>Henry</hi> the Emperour to be declared an enemy to the Church, and degraded him of his Imperiall dignity. The King of <hi>England,</hi> ſeeing this Councell was held in <hi>France,</hi> compoſed chiefly of the <hi>Gallicane</hi> Church, deſirous to ouer-maſter <hi>Louis</hi> the King of <hi>France,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſes his ſonne in Law the Emperour, to ſet vpon him (as the Popes chiefe piller) on one ſide, and he would aſſaile him on the other; The Emperour eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wrought to ſuch a buſineſſe, prepares all his beſt forces: the King of <hi>England</hi> doth the like.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:3007:35"/>
            <p> The King of <hi>France,</hi> ſeeing this ſtorme comming ſo impetuouſly vpon him, wrought ſo with the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Germante,</hi> as they taking into their conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the future miſchiefe of a warre raſhly, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduiſedly taken, with the importance of a kinde neighbourhood, aduiſed the Emperour not to enter thereinto, till he had ſignified to the King of <hi>France</hi> the cauſes of his diſcontent; Whereupon Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours were diſpatched to the King of <hi>France,</hi> who anſwers, that he grieued much to ſee the two grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt pillers of the Church thus ſhaken with thoſe diſſentions, which might hazzard the ruine of the whole Frame; that he was a friend to them both, and would labour and endeauour all he could to mediate an attonement, rather then adde fewell to a fire too fierce already, which he deſired to extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh for the good and quiet of Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p>This Ambaſſage and anſwer ſo tooke, that the Emperour was diuerted from his former reſolution, and was glad to haue <hi>Louis</hi> a mediator of the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord betweene the Pope and him, which ſhortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was concluded at <hi>Wormes,</hi> for the Popes aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, to whom the Emperour yeelds vp the right of the inueſtitures of Biſhops and other benefices.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>England</hi> expecting great matters to haue riſen by this buſineſſe, was highly diſpleaſed, being ſo diſappointed of the Emperours aſſiſtance; proceedes notwithſtanding in his intentions againſt <hi>Louis.</hi> Betweene them there were many great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts, with the expence of much bloud, and charges, (which is the onely fruit warre affordeth) but in the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:3007:35"/>end both wearied and tyred out, a peace was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded.</p>
            <p>Then of late yeares (as it hath beene here formerly related) in the raigne of King <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond, there was enmity and open warres betweene Pope <hi>Paul</hi> and the Spaniard. The Pope beſieged and confined with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the walls of <hi>Rome</hi> by Duke <hi>Alua;</hi> relieued by the French King, yet fell from him, and reconciled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the Spaniard, as to the ſtronger ſide.</p>
            <p>That the Pope cannot erre in matter of faith; his power to depoſe Kings, and diſpoſe of Kingdomes; are two mayne poſitions the Papiſts holde: both which, I humbly leaue, to our Diuines to deale with them therein. But for thoſe two particulars here now mentioned, and many other former paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Pope, the vulgar may iudge. In the time of Queene <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> did familiarly and freely giue Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricks in <hi>Ireland:</hi> but thoſe that had them ſo gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, could neuer gaine poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>Then farther, there can be no ſuch feares &amp; doubts for the alteration of Religion, as is apprehended, if we take into conſideration theſe particulars follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</p>
            <p>Firſt, we hauing a well ordered and well gouerned Kingdome, where Religion is eſtabliſhed, Rites and Ceremonies ordained, and by a long vſe and cuſtome receiued and confirmed; the many apparent proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities of the Kings integrity, the many rare and worthy learned men that are in the Kingdome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered.</p>
            <p>The King, though Prince-like for his recreations,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:3007:36"/>and that his affections haue beene caried with ſome delights and pleaſures; yet hath he been ſo ſtudious, that he is learned beyond expectation, and cuſtome of great Princes: and for his integrity, it is of fifty ſeauen yeares growth, hath made thereof many religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous &amp; worthy expreſſions both by his learned works, and words, and indeede hath ſhot ſuch arrowes, which will hang in the ſides of the Romiſh Religion in after ages, as he is Defender of the Faith by title, he will ſo continue in truth.</p>
            <p>The firſt that had the Title, was <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, giuen him by Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth, for writing againſt <hi>Luther.</hi> After his conuerſion and ſuppreſſion of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, yet retayned he that ſtile, and afterwards during the raignes of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, the late famous Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and our now Soueraigne, it hath beene continued, and doubtleſſe by him will be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</p>
            <p>Amongſt many his worthy expreſſions of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe therein in one of his workes, he thus declareth: that it is one of the principall parts of the duty which appertaines to a Chriſtian King, to protect his true Church within his owne Dominions: to extirpate hereſies is a maxime without all controuerſies. In which reſpect, thoſe honourable titles of <hi>Cuſtos, Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex vtriuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tabulae,</hi> keeper and reuenger of both tables of the law, and <hi>Nutricius Eccleſiae,</hi> nurſing Father of the Church, doe rightly belong to euery Emperour, King, and Chriſtian Monarch: ſo that there is no queſtion or imagination, that he will ſuffer the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion now profeſſed, to come vnder the Egiptian ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitude
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:3007:36"/>of the Pope: But rather will be like a goodly Caedar tree, of full growth, irremoueable, not to be otherwiſe, or other where ſet or planted: vnder whom his Subiects ſhall ſit ſafe and protected. Our hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Prince, a branch thereof, will be of the like kinde, affording the ſame fruit, who doubtleſſe will now be the more precious in that kinde, in reſpect of his late trauell and triall, longed for the ſweet comfort, and preaching of the Goſpell (according to the ſaying of the Pſalmiſt) euen as the thirſty Hart did for the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Brook: Though he hath bin amongſt the Sirens, his eares would admit no audience: a ſound was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in them, as if hee heard his religeous Father King <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaking vnto him,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Chro.</hi> 28.9.</note> as ſometimes holy <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpake vnto his ſonne <hi>Salomon:</hi> And thou <hi>Charles</hi> my ſonne, know thou the God of thy Father, &amp; ſerue him with a perfect heart, and with a willing mind; for the Lord ſearcheth all the hearts, and vnderſtandeth all the imaginations of the thoughts; if thou ſeeke him, he will be found of thee; if thou forſake him, he will caſt thee off for euer: all which ſerued onely but as addition. Our Prince his integrity is ſuch, ſo firmely ſettled in the true Religion now profeſſed, that there was no poſſibility of his alteration. For which, we are infinitely bound vnto God, and an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible happineſſe it is to the Kingdome, that his diſpoſition, all his courſes and carriages af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fording all Royall and Princely vertues (as indeede meerely compoſed thereof) his patience farre excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his paſſion, which bringeth peace to himſelfe, and victory ouer others; free from all imperfections
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:3007:37"/>that Princes many times are ſubiect vnto, the more hauing no ſtrict nor diſciplinated education, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſoothed and flattered in all they ſay or doe.</p>
            <p>What an exceeding great comfort and ioy may we take to ſee his willing heart, and ready hand to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the Petitions and complaints of the poore di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed Subiects, and his gracious diſpoſition to ſee them relieued? which doubtleſſe will occaſion the whole progreſſion of his life, to bee much the more happy and proſperous, gaine him bleſſed fame, and euerlaſting memory, and a Crowne of glory in a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Poſitiuely our King and Prince, the one for pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall affection, the other for <hi>filial</hi> obedience, for after ages may be worthy patternes.</p>
            <p>That by the Spaniſh Lady her comming ouer, the Proteſtant Religion ſhould be any wayes endange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, or ſubiect to alteration, there is not ſo much likelihood, as probability ſhe may come to be a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, for theſe reaſons following: the effects of true loue are great, and the rather, ſhe being a young ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Princeſſe, and farre from her owne Country and friends, amongſt whom ſhe hath bin bred, and now come to haue others new, and liuing in their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, ſhe may of her owne accord by degrees haue her affections incorporated amongſt them; borne and bred amidſt the pleaſures and delights of the Court, accuſtomed to Royall Courtſhip, may much farther it. Townes before they yeeld, doe vſually parle; That the Lady neither can nor will auoyde, and then ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſo pleaſing an obiect to the eye, and ſo Royall
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:3007:37"/>an affailant in ſuch a perſon as our hopefull Prince is. Theſe things may goe neere the point to doe it: Then her Ladies and Maydes of Honour, which of like at the firſt, will be the Cabinets of her Councell, and other her followers, though Sermons they will not heare, yet when in daily diſcourſes they ſhall haue ſuch ſiege and battery laide to their Romiſh Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by an Army of reuerend Biſhops, Doctors, and many famous learned Preachers in that kinde, the whole forces of our Kingdomes; aſſuredly it will ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther looſe ground then gaine any: the proper nature of Religion, is farre ſooner to be perſwaded by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, then forced by conſtraint. Thoſe are the two things that Religion ſtands on: the world cannot create a new creature, be it neuer ſo little: So no law of man, nor compulſion can make a good Chriſtian in heart, without inward grace: wherein the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter is to perſwade, and leaue the ſucceſſe to God. More famous, learned, and worthier men, no age euer afforded: who will be a glory to the age: The King, and they, as the Sunne and Moone, and ſome others of the Clergie, as leſſer Starres will make perfection of light, though they contribute ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what leſſe, will make the light of the Goſpell in the courſe and manner as it is now profeſſed, ſhine ſo bright, that it ſhall dimme all Romiſh ſuperſtition and Idolatry, as the bleſſed Sunne doth a burning Taper: and there ſhall be no ſuch Curtaine drawne to keepe out the light, but that it ſhall ſhine ouer the whole face of the earth, that wee ſhall ſee their good workes, and bee taught by them to glorifie
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:3007:38"/>our heauenly Father.</p>
            <p>The two famous Vniuerſities, the Spheares from whence learning, and ſo conſequently the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Religion, hath his motion, they will not be ecclipſed. Let vs be confident, that our <hi>Ioſuah</hi> and his Clergie being of his houſe, will profeſſe (whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer other Nations doe) hee and they will ſerue the Lord. If any of the Clergie, when they ſhall come to the touch, proue not right (as peraduenture ſome of them may not;) it will be ſaid of them, Yee chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> weepe, and lament, that for want of courage you betray your Maſter.</p>
            <p>So in concluſion, wiſhing the countrie people, from henceforth in their reſolutions would be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and not to trouble themſelues as now they doe, in their expoſtulations of our Princes royall match, nor take vpon them to foreknow and preiudicate, that dangers may enſue, either for matters of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or gouernment, but abandon all doubts, and diſpaire of thoſe things, and rather take it to their comforts, hopes, or rather indeed aſſurances, that all thoſe things formerly related, will rather ſo come to paſſe then otherwiſe; and that there will be no more ſuch rubbes in the paſſages of State af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires as late haue beene, but will runne ſmoothe, as formerly they haue done, and all dealings and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages betweene man and man, will come againe into their courſe and current, and the Iron age we haue lately liued in will haue an end, which may be the beginning of a golden world; ſo ſoone as it ſhall pleaſe God, our Princes royall match be once ſetled.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:3007:38"/>For his ſafe returne, and the aſſurance wee haue of his integritie, with vnanimous hearts, let vs giue God hearty thankes, and pray that his mariage may bring with it glory to him on high, peace and good will to thoſe on earth, and all happineſſe and ioy to his Highneſſe, to the compleat comfort, content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and good of the King and kingdome, and to Reigne many yeares, honouring the age wee now liue in, with the merits of their wiſedomes and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grities; and finally, that their ſelicities in this world, may ouertake that in the next, and make them weare perpetuall Crownes of Gods glory and their owne, and that ſucceſſiuely their Royall Progenies may ſit vpon the thrones of their kingdomes, euen to the worlds end.</p>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
